<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise ful of consolation for all that are afflicted in minde, or bodie, or otherwise Which armeth vs against impatiencie vnder any crosse. By Nicolas Bovvnde Doctor of Divinitie.</title>
            <author>Bownd, Nicholas, d. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 656:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise ful of consolation for all that are afflicted in minde, or bodie, or otherwise Which armeth vs against impatiencie vnder any crosse. By Nicolas Bovvnde Doctor of Divinitie.</title>
                  <author>Bownd, Nicholas, d. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 173, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Cantrell Legge, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A comfortable treatise for the afflicted.</note>
                  <note>Also issued at part 2 of: Bownd, Nicholas.  The unbeleefe of S. Thomas the apostle, laid open (STC 3441.5 sq.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:15176:1"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 51. l. 15. for rather, read either. p. 53. l. 4. for The, This. p. 55. l. for note, roote. p. 65. l. 4. dele, not. p. 98. l. 10. for vſe, inioy. p. 101. l. 7. for walke, waſh. p. 108. l. 20. dele, that. p. 109. l. 7. deeſt, to. p. 119. l. <hi>vlt.</hi> for that, if. p. 120. l. 3. deeſt, to. p. 140. l. 11. for turning, curing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15176:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE FVL OF CONSOLATION for all that are afflicted in minde, <hi>or bodie, or otherwiſe.</hi> Which armeth vs againſt impatiencie <hi>vnder any croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By NICOLAS BOVVNDE Doctor <hi>of Divinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lament. Ierem. 4.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>It is good for a man, that he beare the yoke in his youth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by CANTRELL LEGGE, Printer to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15176:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15176:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right Worſhipfull Sir</hi> HENRIE WARNER Knight, and to <hi>the vertuous Ladie</hi> FRANCIS WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER his Chriſtian and godly wife, <hi>the daily increaſe of that true godlines,</hi> that hath the promiſes of this <hi>life, and of the life</hi> to come.</head>
            <p>RIght Worſhipfull Sir, in reſpect of your place indeede, ſome learned Treatiſe of Iustice might haue ſeemed more fitting: which if I had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, I could haue added nothing vnto that, which you daily practiſe, and haue done many yeares, to the great good of that part of our countrey, wherein God hath placed you. But yet, as you are a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and a profeſſor of the Goſpel, and ſo (euen in the multitude of Gods bleſsings, many waies, and plentifully powred out
<pb facs="tcp:15176:3"/> vpon you) are ſubiect with all the reſt of Gods children, vnto ſome afflictions and croſſes; this argument, I hope, for the time preſent, or to come, may ſeeme not altogether vnſeaſonable. Seeing that the Lord hath ſaide, that <hi>if any man will follow him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 16.24</note> 
               <hi>he muſt take vp his croſſe and follow him.</hi> And therefore that is it, which euery one muſt looke for, at one time or an other, and in what kind it ſhall ſeeme beſt to his heauenly wiſdome. For here I haue laboured, to ſhew out of the word of God, many reaſons of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and comfortable bearing of the ſame. But whatſoeuer it be, it proceedeth from an heart vnfainedly well wiſhing vnto you: and ſo I pray you accept of it, as an apparant teſtimonie of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And for your ſelfe, good Madame, though your owne vertues and kindnes deſerue much, God hauing put vpon you that <hi>crowne of glorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 16.31.</note> that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of, namely, that <hi>your age is found in the way of righteouſnes,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:15176:3"/> in theſe moſt corrupt and dangerous times: yet the worthie memorie of M. <hi>Robert Foorth</hi> ſometimes of Butly, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire,<note place="margin">Prou. 2 17.</note> heretofore <hi>the guide of your youth,</hi> your ſelfe beeing ioyned vnto him in the neereſt <hi>couenant of God,</hi> had beene ſufficient to mooue me among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his friends and allies, to ſhew what te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of loue I could vnto any of his.</p>
            <p>Whoſe zeale to the Goſpel of Chriſt, and loue to all, that profeſſed it: with his ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in executing of iuſtice, heartie affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all his neighbours; great hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and releefe to the poore, euen in the times of greateſt ſcarſitie and want; with moſt excellent orders in his family for daily praier, for reading the Scriptures, and for ſinging of Pſalmes, doe yet ſpeake for him, and ſhall whiles this age remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Whoſe vprightneſſe of heart vnto God (wherein he was <hi>a right Nathanael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.47.</note> euen <hi>a true Iſraelite indeed</hi>) I pray God, that all his right worſhipfull children, ſonnes and daughters may ſet before their
<pb facs="tcp:15176:4"/> eyes, as an example to follow.</p>
            <p>And ſo praying God to bleſſe you both, with many comfortable daies together in this life, and eternall happines after death in the kingdome of heauen, neuer to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered: with the like bleſsing of God vpon the right worſhipfull your children, and childrens children on both ſides, I bid you all moſt humbly and heartily fare-well in Chriſt. <hi>Norton in Suff. Iun. 24. 1608.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all vnfained loue for Chriſts ſake,</hi> Nicolas Bownde.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag 19. l. 5. read, that God. 25.4 r. mixt thing. 27.20. r. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 9 r. our ſelues. 33.16. r. infirmities. 42.20. <hi>deeſt</hi> are. 24. r. rich mercie. 47.11. r. want. 53.7. r. meaning. 57.18. r. fauour of God. 62 3. r. ſearing. 99. 5. after man, put in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15176:4"/>
            <head>A COMFORTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE TREATISE for the afflicted.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.26, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: for we know not what to pray as we ought: but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh request for vs with ſighes, which cannot be expreſſed. <hi>27</hi> But he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the meaning of the Spirit: for he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth request for the Saints, according to the will of God. <hi>28</hi> Alſo we know that all things worke together for the best vnto them that loue God: euen to them that are called of his purpoſe. <hi>29</hi> For thoſe whome he knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he alſo predeſtinate to be made like to the image of his Sonne, that he might be the first borne among many brethren, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe generall intent and purpoſe of the Apoſtle here is, to intreat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15176:5"/> of the matter of afflictions, to this ende, that he might ſhew, that none of them ſhall be able to hinder vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſaluation, that ſo beeing well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of them, and of the goodnes of God towards vs in them, we might be the better prepared for them, and haue more comfort in the bearing of them. For he hauing prooued before, that we are iuſtified &amp; ſaued by faith in Chriſt, for the further aſſurance of all thoſe that relie vpon Chriſt for their ſaluation, he remooueth out of their minds, thoſe things that might ſeeme to weaken their faith herein.</p>
            <p>And namely, firſt of all the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our naturall corruption, cleauing faſt vnto vs; hindering vs from that which is good, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to that that is euill, euen after ſuch time, as we do beleeue: of which he hath ſpoken in the former chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Rom. 7 15.</note> ſaying, I allow not that which I doe: for what I would, that doe I not:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15176:5"/> but what I hate, that do I. For I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no good: for to will is preſent with me, but I finde no meanes to performe that that is good. For I doe not the good, that I would, but the euill that I would not, that doe I. I finde then, that when I would doe good, I am thus yoaked, that euill is preſent with me. For I delight in the law of God in the inner man. But I ſee an other law in my members re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the law of my minde, and leading me captiue vnto the law of ſinne which is in my members. O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from the bodie of this death!</p>
            <p>For anſwer vnto which he ſaith, that by the imputation of the perfect holineſſe of our Sauiour Chriſt, the guiltines of this is taken away, and is not imputed vnto vs before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of God: and therefore he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15176:6"/> ſaith,<note place="margin">verſ. 17.</note> it is no more I that doe it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me: for if I doe that I would not, it is no more I that doe it, but the ſinne that dwelleth in me: and therefore it ſhall not be laid vnto my charge:<note place="margin">and 25.</note> for I my ſelfe in my minde ſerue the law of God: though in my fleſh I ſerue the law of ſinne: and therefore in the next chapter he breaketh out into this comfortable ſaying, and auoucheth it moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that there is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> but after the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And this communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that herein we haue with Chriſt for the diſcharging of vs from the guilt of our naturall corruption, we know by two infallible tokens: the one is the Spirit of ſanctification, which we haue receiued from him, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that we walk not afrer the fleſh any more,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15176:6"/> but after the Spirit.<note place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> For if the Spirit of him that raiſed vp Ieſus from the dead, dwell in vs: he that raiſed vp Chriſt from the dead, ſhall alſo quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our mortall bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in vs:<note place="margin">13.</note> and therefore if we mortifie the deedes of the bodie by the Spirit, we ſhall liue: for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are lead by the Spirit of God, they are the ſonnes of God: and thus this ſanctification of ours, which is in ſinceritie and truth, though in much weaknes and great imperfection pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Spirit of God, is a ſure token that we are partakers of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt to the perfect iuſtifying of vs in the ſight of God, and to the taking away of all the remnants of ſinne inhering &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs continually.</p>
            <p>The ſecond teſtimonie hereof is the Spirit of adoption, which he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs, to aſſure vs of his fauour, and to deliuer vs from our feares in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15176:7"/> and to teach vs chearefully and comfortably to pray vnto God, as to our moſt merciful Father: for he ſaith that this ſpirit of ſanctification,<note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> is not the ſpirit of bondage, to feare again: which feare is wrought in vs by the ſight of our ſinnes through the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the law: but it is the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we crie, Abba, Father, that is, it ſealeth vp our adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our mindes, and ſo openeth our mouthes in prayer vnto God: and therefore he addeth: that the ſame Spirit beareth witnes with our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that wee are the children of God: and if wee be children, wee are alſo heires, euen the heires of God, and heires annexed with Chriſt. Thus by the Spirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, which is diſcerned by this moſt excellent operation of his, that it cauſeth vs to pray in hope to God, as to our father, and to call him not once father after a faint manner, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15176:7"/> twiſe or thriſe; yea continually, Abba, father, or father, father: we know that we haue our part in Chriſt, for whoſe ſake onely he is our father, and ſo are by him deliuered from the guiltines of all the remnants of corruption &amp; ſinne, though they are in our fleſh, and dwell there continually, as the Apoſtle ſaith: and doe ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues both by vnbeleefe, and by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doing of that good that we would, and cauſing vs to doe that euill that we would not.</p>
            <p>Another thing whereby our faith is aſſaulted and often weakened, is the conſideration of thoſe manifold and grieuous afflictions which may and doe befal vs in this world; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it might ſeeme vnto vs, that our waies are not ſo acceptable vnto the Lord, that we might haue comfort in them. For anſwer vnto which, hee ſheweth, that of what nature or kind ſoeuer they be, they ſhall bee ſo farre
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15176:8"/> from hindering vs from the fauour of God, &amp; from our ſaluation; as that in them wee haue Chriſt Ieſus, who went before vs in all our afflictions, further then wee can, and yet at the laſt came vnto glorie: and therefore if we patiently abide, as we haue not onely the Prophets, and Apoſtles, &amp; Martyrs, and other holy men; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Chriſt himſelfe to be our fellow in them; ſo we ſhall be fellowes with him, &amp; like vnto him in glorie: for he ſaith,<note place="margin">16.</note> If ſo be that we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him.</p>
            <p>And leaſt that it might ſeem grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vnto vs, to goe to ſo happie an eſtate through ſo grieuous &amp; painfull a way, and ſo might thinke, that the kingdome of heauen, though it bee neuer ſo pretious in it ſelf, we ſhould buie it too deerely; he telleth vs aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, that by conſidering the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of this world on the one ſide, and the felicitie of the kingdome of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15176:8"/> heauen on the other ſide, and ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vp the account of the one and the other, hee hath found the totall ſumme of them both to bee ſo farre differing, that all the afflictions of this miſerable and wretched world indured by any, and from the firſt houre of their birth, vnto their laſt breath, are not to bee compared in greatneſſe or continuance, vnto that glorie and happineſſe that ſhall there be reuealed and beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, according to the expreſſe wordes of the text: I count,<note place="margin">verſ. 18.</note> or all things beeing well conſidered, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the afflictions of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, are not worthie of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And as this glorie is thus great, ſo it is moſt ſure and certaine, though we doe not preſently enioy it; and therefore we need not in any wiſe to doubt of it: for all the other creatures of God, beſides man, which are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15176:9"/> and dumbe, haue in their kind a certaine ſenſe and feeling of it; for though they bee now ſubiect, (and that yet but for a time) vnto this vanitie, that is, corruption and abuſe, which they are in: yet by the inſtinct of nature they doe moſt earneſtly, &amp; as it were with their heads lifted vp, and neckes ſtretched out, that they might ſee a great way off, looke for the reuealing of the ſonnes of God, that ſo they themſelues alſo might then be redeemed from bondage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their glorious libertie; and they ſhall not bee diſappointed of their hope. Therefore much more we that haue receiued the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, ſhould with greater patience in trouble abide the will of God a while, and with more certaintie and earneſtneſſe of deſire looke for an happy change of all our afflictions in that moſt glorious day.</p>
            <p>Which the Apoſtle ſetteth out in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15176:9"/> much more patheticall and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant wordes then I haue expreſſed, and therefore I could not paſſe them ouer; for he ſaith,<note place="margin">and 19.</note> The feruent deſire of the creature, that is, of the whole frame of this world, and of all things in it, waiteth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonnes of God ſhall bee reuealed. 20. Becauſe the creature is ſubiect vnto vanitie, not of his owne will, or natural inclination, but by reaſon of him which hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued it vnder hope. For though hee did by his curſe vpon all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which he had made for man, ſhew how greatly he was diſpleaſed with the fall and ſinne of man, yet he would giue them hope to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and therefore he addeth, 21. For the creature alſo ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of corruption in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God. For we know that euery cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature groaneth with vs alſo, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth in paine together vnto this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15176:10"/> preſent: as a woman with child, not onely with exceeding ſorrowe, but with hope of a comfortable deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in time. And not onely the creatures, but we alſo which haue the firſt fruits of the Spirit, euen we doe ſigh in our ſelues, waiting for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption euen the redemption of our owne bodies, that is, our laſt reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, when as our adoption ſhall be fully accompliſhed in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
            <p>Which condition of ours in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though grieuous for a time, but moſt happie in the ende, that we might not refuſe to vndergoe, with the reſt of the creatures, and our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren &amp; ſiſters: he calleth vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the wiſe order which God hath appointed in ſauing of vs, which is by hope:<note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> for he ſaith, We are ſaued by hope, but hope that is ſeene is not hope: for how can a man hope for that he ſeeth, but if we hope for that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15176:10"/> we ſee not, we doe with patience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide for it. Therefore we muſt not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine ſo ſoone to inioy all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as we beleeue it: but be content to want all things for a time: that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for them with patience &amp; long-ſuffering, we might come to them at laſt: vnleſſe we will goe about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert this excellent order, which the Lord hath determined and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be in ſauing vs; which is by trayning vs vp in the hope and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of all things promiſed for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>But now becauſe the hope that is deferred, is the fainting of the heart, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that is,<note place="margin">Prou. 13.12.</note> it maketh a man ſick at the very heart, to be long deferred of that that we deſire and hope for: &amp; therefore we might feare both in reſpect of our own weaknes, and alſo the greatnes, together with the long continuance of affliction, that we ſhould not with patience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15176:11"/> the croſſe continue to hold out happily vnto the ende: he further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for our ſingular comfort, that the Spirit, which we haue receiued, whereby we are ſanctified, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we pray to God, as to our Father, ſhall performe this office alſo vnto vs, that it ſhall helpe to beare the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of our affliction with vs; and ſo though we be neuer ſo weake, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſupported by the power of it, we ſhall bee able to endure them well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for hee ſaith, Likewiſe the ſpirit alſo helpeth our infirmities.</p>
            <p>So that it ſhall be all one with vs, as with a young childe, vpon whoſe ſhoulder the father laying a heauie burden, which of it ſelfe were able to preſſe him downe to the ground; hee ſhould ſo put his hand vnder it, that hee ſhould beare the whole waight almoſt and ſtreſſe of it himſelfe, and ſo he ſhould make him carry it. Now if the earthly father wil not of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15176:11"/> affection ouerlade the poore childe, then wee neede not to feare, but that the Lord our ſpiritual father will ſo increaſe our ſtrength, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of our afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that we ſhall find this promiſe to be true by experience, That his holy ſpirit ſhall helpe our infirmities.</p>
            <p>And thus <hi>Dauid</hi> commendeth the mercie of God vnto vs,<note place="margin">Pſ. 103.13.</note> That as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath compaſſion on his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo hath the Lord compaſſion on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him: he knoweth whereof we be made, he remembreth that we be but duſt: where hee rendreth this one reaſon of the merciful dealing of God towards vs, euen the knowledge that he hath of our weake and fraile eſtate; which thing, as it is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to conſider, ſo we ſhall finde it to be moſt true by experience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt hath praied for vs, as himſelfe witneſſeth in the Goſpel, vnto his heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15176:12"/> that he would giue vs a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that might abide with vs for euer;<note place="margin">Iob. 14.16.</note> euen the ſpirit of truth, whom the world cannot receiue.</p>
            <p>And the bleſſed Apoſtle confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of himſelfe, that he was partaker of the fruit of this praier; for beeing in many afflictions that were able to haue ouercom him, yet by the power of Gods ſpirit, he did hold out hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in them:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.5.</note> ſaying, Wee are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on euery ſide, yet are wee not in diſtreſſe; we are in doubt, but we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire not; we are perſecuted, but not forſaken; we are caſt downe, but wee periſh not: Euery where we beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in our bodie the dying of the lord Ieſus, that the life of Ieſus might alſo be made manifeſt in our bodies; for we which liue, are alwaies deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto death for Ieſus ſake, that the life alſo of Ieſus might bee made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in our bodies. Where he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the miſerable eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15176:12"/> that the faithfull, and more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Miniſters are in, vnto a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall dying, and the vertues of the ſpirit of God in them vnto life, which oppreſſeth that death: &amp; he rendreth this reaſon, why the Lord doth thus often afflict his ſeruants, namly,<note place="margin">verſ. 7.</note> That the excellencie of that power might be of God, and not of vs, that is, that all men might perceiue howe they ſtood not by mans power, but by the ſingular vertue of God, in that they die a thouſand deaths, but neuer pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: and ſo in many daungers as hee defendeth them, ſo in much weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he vpholdeth them, and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit helpeth their infirmities.</p>
            <p>And this grace of God alſo vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him in great weakneſſe againſt moſt dangerous temptations he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth in an other place: for when he felt himſelfe ſo ſore troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with them to his continuall grief, as if he had had a pricke thruſt into<note place="margin">chap. 12.7.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15176:13"/> his fleſh; and the meſſenger of Satan did ſo moleſt him, as though he had beene moſt ſhamefully buffetted on the face: for which he beſought the Lord thriſe, that is, very often, that it might depart from him: he receiued this anſwer from God,<note place="margin">verſ. 9.</note> My grace is ſufficient for thee; for my power is made perfect through weaknes. So in this ſpirituall combate, the Spirit of God did vphold him againſt the temptations of Satan, and of his own corruption: and ſo he concludeth, that when he was weake, then was he ſtrong: that is, in his greateſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he felt the power of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding him; and ſo ſhall wee, if wee waite vpon him.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle ſheweth that this which hee found by experience in himſelfe, by the goodnes and mercie of God, belongeth to all the reſt of the faithfull, when he writeth thus to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> God is faithful, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15176:13"/> will not ſuffer you to bee tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that you be able, but will euen giue the iſſue with the temptation, that you may bee able to beare it: where he ſaith, The God that would haue vs tempted for our good, wil by his ſpirit ſo ſtrengthen vs, that wee ſhall be able to beare them, and haue an happie iſſue out of them. And if there were no Scripture to prooue it, our owne experience might tell vs the truth of it; for if wee haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any thing, wee may remember that many times wee haue beene brought very lowe, and haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone ſuch hard brunts, that wee thought we ſhould neuer haue beene able to haue borne them. Neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſhould we, but that there was another thing in vs, farre aboue our ſelues, which did helpe vs, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs both to indure, and to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe things, which we thoght wee ſhould haue fainted in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15176:14"/> of them: and ſo we may boldly ſay with this holy Apoſtle, Bleſſed be God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.</note> euen the father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the father of mercies and God of all comforts; which comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in all our tribulations, that we may be able to comfort them that be in affliction, with the comfort wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we our ſelues are comforted of God. For as the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in vs, ſo our conſolation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus the Lord increaſeth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of his Spirit in his ſeruants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their afflictions, ſo that they doe not onely equall them, but alſo exceede them in time: and ſo beeing ſupported by the Spirit, they are able to beare them. And this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, that his Spirit ſhall help vs in our infirmities, is ſo much the more worthie to be conſidered of vs, becauſe it is ſo generall, that it ſhall helpe vs, not in ſome few onely, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15176:14"/> in all our infirmities whatſoeuer: for he ſpeaketh indefinitly, and not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the promiſe to any one. So that there can be no weakeneſſe in vs ſo great, or infirmities ſo many vpon vs, in which the Spirit ſhal not ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs, euen to the bearing of the greateſt croſſe, that God ſhall lay vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; as we haue ſeene it in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle before, who ſaid, that God did comfort him in all his tribulations, and his conſolations in Chriſt did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, euen as his ſufferings did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound.</p>
            <p>But in the meane ſeaſon <hi>Paul</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to vnderſtand, that the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Gods children are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo great, that they farre paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrength that is in vs to beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and that we are not able to doe it of our ſelues: yea, that we are very weak of our ſelues, and ſubiect to many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, though we haue receiued the Spirit of ſanctification, and of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15176:15"/> for the ſame Spirit doth not cleane ridde vs of them, whiles wee are in this world, but doth onely help vs in them: according to the expreſſe words of the Apoſtle, Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities. In ſo much that he confeſſeth not onely of other the faithfull, but alſo of the Apoſtles, and of himſelfe, in whoſe name he ſpeaketh, and ioyneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with them, that they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to haue vndergone ſo many and great things, as they did, being fraile men like vnto vs, but that they had the Spirit helping them in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: for hee doth not ſay, that the Spirit helpeth your weaknes, but vs, that are the ſtrongeſt, and helpeth vs in our infirmities: then no man muſt thinke to be free from them, it is and muſt be ſufficient for vs that the Spirit doth helpe vs in them.</p>
            <p>The truth of which may likewiſe appeare in the great complaint of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15176:15"/> 
               <hi>Dauid, Iob,</hi> and the reſt of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, who though they did patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beare many great things, yet not without the bewraying of many great infirmities in themſelues: for <hi>Iob</hi> though he be commended vnto vs as a moſt tried patterne of all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; yet how many and great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities appeared in him it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, when he thus cried out againſt himſelfe, Let the day periſh,<note place="margin">Iob 3.3.</note> wherein I was borne, and the night when it was ſaid, there is a man child concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: let that day be darkneſſe, let not God regard it from aboue, neither let the light ſhine vpon it: and why died I not in the birth? or why died I not when I came out of the womb? why did the knees preuent me? and why did I ſucke the breaſts? and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſuch bitter wordes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from great weakneſſe he vttered againſt himſelfe. And <hi>Dauid,</hi> though he was a man after Gods own heart,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.13</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15176:16"/> and did beare many afflictions vnder <hi>Saul</hi> with great patience;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.13.</note> yet in many Pſalmes he bewraieth great infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.22.</note> I ſaid in mine haſt, I am caſt out of thy ſight; he acknowledgeth his infidelitie to be ſuch, that he did raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay that God had cleane forſaken him: and in an other place he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus of himſelfe; I ſaide in my feare,<note place="margin">&amp; 116.11.</note> All men are lyars, that is, he ſaid in his temptation, that <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, when he told him, that hee ſhould bee King of Iſrael, did not ſpeake it from God by the ſpirit of propheſie, but of his owne head, and ſo did but lie and diſſemble with him.</p>
            <p>Therefore we are not to imagine of ſuch a portion of Gods Spirit, that might ſwallow vp all our infirmities, and cleane ridde vs of them, (for then we ſhould be no men) but it muſt be ſufficient, that we are aided with the ſtrength of it, ſo that we finally fall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15176:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> not downe, and lie ſtil vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burden of affliction, yeilding to our infirmities, and ſo ouercome of them: ſo that there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>xt thing, as it were in vs; namely, our owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities to humble vs, and the ſtrength of Gods Spirit to inable vs to beare our afflictions. So that hauing ſo ſtrong and ſo able an helper, to beare with vs the burden, we may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted with hope of induring the greateſt thing, that may befall vs in this world, though continuing vpon vs neuer ſo long. Not indeed alwaies in that manner, that we ought, and doe deſire, but ſo as it may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto God, and ſo farre forth as his holy Spirit ſhall helpe vs in our infirmities: for though there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in vs but infirmities, yet there is helpe for vs from the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>And that we might euen in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, by the helpe of the Spirit of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15176:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> God beare all afflictions as we ought, the Apoſtle further addeth, that the ſame Spirit ſhall likewiſe ſtirre vs vp in all neceſſities of ours, to pray vnto God for helpe, and for his grace, and to make our moane vnto him, as to our father, and we ſhall be heard of him therin,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> ſaying, For we know not what to pray as wee ought: but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh requeſt for vs with ſighes, which cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but he that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the meaning of the Spirit: for he maketh requeſt for the Saints, according to the will of God. Where we ſee, both what great infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities we be ſubiect vnto, and alſo how the Spirit of God helpeth vs in the ſame. For ſometimes through the greatneſſe of our miſerie, we know not what to ſay, or howe to pray to God as we ought: and yet then his Spirit doth ſtirre vp in vs, though not many wel ordered ſpeches or words;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15176:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet thoſe ſighes and groanes which beeing vnſpeakable, and not felt of them, in whom they are, are well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and accepted of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they proceede from his ſpirit, whoſe meaning he knoweth &amp; gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, becauſe it maketh requeſt for the Saints according to the will of God.</p>
            <p>Wherein we are firſt of all to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that though wee haue receiued the ſpirit of God, euen the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we crie Abba, Father, which ſpirit teacheth vs to pray, and by which wee haue many times called vpon God with great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance and comfort, both for and with our ſelues and others alſo; yet there may be a time, &amp; that very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, wherein wee may be ſo diſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome great affliction, and in ſuch a caſe, that beeing as it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed and ouercome with the greatneſſe and ſtrangeneſſe of it, wee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15176:18"/> cannot well tel what to pray, or what to aske of God. And though prayer at ſuch a time eſpecially be our only refuge, according to the ſaying of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.25.</note> Call vpon me in the day of trouble, ſo wil I deliuer thee: yet we cannot tell how to begin, and what to ſay. And ſo vnlike ſhall we bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Father, and to that that wee haue beene in times paſt, as though wee were not the ſame: nay, our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate may ſeeme to bee like vnto the wicked, who are at their wits ende, and know not how to pray vnto God at all. For if we were asked then, what we would haue, we cannot make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect anſwer; and though we haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to aske of God according to our neede, yet wee cannot vſe it: for we cannot tell what to pray.</p>
            <p>O what a wonderfull thing is this! but yet moſt true; and that which is to be found not in ſome fewe meane perſons onely, that are ignorant, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15176:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue not accuſtomed themſelues to prayer; but in the moſt excellent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, euen the Apoſtles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; as <hi>Paul</hi> here bringeth himſelfe in with the reſt for an example, and in this great infirmitie maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like vnto the reſt, ſaying; For we know not what to pray as we ought. And though there be many excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t praiers in the old &amp; new Teſtament, by which wee might learne how to pray; and eſpecially wee haue a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect forme of prayer preſcribed by our Sauiour Chriſt to direct vs in all things needfull for vs: yet in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wee aske thoſe things many times, which if we had them, would bee hurtfull vnto vs: and when wee doe aske that that is profitable and good, yet euen then by preſcribing vnto the Lord the time when, &amp; the manner how, and the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee would bee deliuered, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our owne minde, wee pray
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15176:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> with ſuch impatience and diſtruſt, that it may be truely ſaid of vs, Wee cannot tell what to pray as wee ought.</p>
            <p>This was the eſtate of that good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when he was ſicke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death; at what time beeing greatly pained in his body, and ſore troubled in his minde, and out of all hope of life, he turned his face vnto the wall, and praied vnto the Lord; but how? hee doth expreſſe it in theſe words. Like a Crane or a Swallow ſo did I chatter,<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.14.</note> I did mourne as a doue: that is, in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule hee did not vſe many words; yea, hee was altogether ſo confuſed, that his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was like the chattering of birdes, he knew not almoſt what to ſay.</p>
            <p>Such was the perplexitie &amp; more then infirmitie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> when as in his great afflictions, in ſtead of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he roared all the day long, as hee ſaith of himſelfe;<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.3.</note> When I helde my
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15176:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> tongue, my bones conſumed, and vvhen I roared all the day: ſo that ſometimes he held his peace, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betvveen hope and deſpaire, and ſometimes he vttered many deſires; but beeing carried avvay vvith the preſent feeling of his aduerſitie, they vvere more like the roarings of a vvilde beaſt, then any vvell ordered prayer. And at another time he ſaith, Mine heart trembleth vvithin me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.4.</note> &amp; the horrors of death are fallen vpon me: feare and trembling are come vpon me, and an horrible feare hath couered me: in vvhich vvords, hee ſhevveth in vvhat infirmity &amp; vveak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he vvas then fallen into: &amp; for his prayers, after vvhat manner they vvere framed, hee declareth in theſe vvordes;<note place="margin">Verſ 2.</note> I mourne in my prayer and make a noiſe, ſo that there vvas mourning and ſome kinde of noiſe, and little elſe. And another time hee expreſſeth his outvvard eſtate, &amp; the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15176:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> inward affection of his mind, and the maner of his prayer then, after this ſort.<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.3.</note> My daies are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed like ſmoak, &amp; my bones are burnt like an herth: mine heart is ſmitten and withered like graſſe, becauſe I forgat to eate my bread: for the voice of my groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my bones doe cleaue to my skinne. I am like a Pellican of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and am like an owle of the deſarts. I watch, and am as a ſparrow alone vpon the houſe top. Surely I haue eaten aſhes as bread, and ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led my drinke with weeping. By which kind of ſpeeches he ſheweth how greatly his affliction did worke vpon him, ſo that in them he did groane and weepe, and caſt out many fearefull cries, but all things were ſo out of order in his praier, that they were like the chattering of a Pelican and of a ſparrow, and the skreeks of an owle, rather then any thing els, if God had conſidered them in his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15176:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſo he might haue reiected them.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee, that theſe moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſeruants of God in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conflicts and agonies, were ſo farre from beeing able to pray vnto God in any tolerable manner, that in their own ſenſe and feeling they did but roare &amp; crie, ſob and ſigh, weepe, mourne and complaine; and that alſo very confuſedly, euen like the Crane, the Swallow, the Pellican, the Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, euen the ſhreeke Owle it ſelfe: ſo diſtracted were they in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and full of diſorder, and fallen into ſo many great diſorders at once. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may not iudge of our ſelues, or of others, by any one ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or few particular caſes, leaſt we ſhould deceiue our ſelues, ſaying, I haue not the ſpirit of God, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pray nor call vpon God in mine affliction; and if I doe at any time, it is not as I ought: for this is that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15176:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> which <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth of himſelfe, &amp; of other the ſeruants of God, and which wee haue ſeene in theſe two excellent Kings, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> that in affliction oftentimes we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what to pray as we ought.</p>
            <p>But yet in this great vnfitneſſe of ours, we muſt not be like to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who then giue ouer all prayer, becauſe they are vnfit for it: and we are ſubiect vnto this temptation, to put off praier, becauſe we ſee that we cannot pray as we ought, and ſo wee are made to thinke, that wee ſhould offend God in praier. But wee muſt then ſtriue earneſtly againſt this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of ours, and ſo pray to God that we might pray; and as the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſaid vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.1.</note> Lord teach vs to pray; ſo let vs deſire the Lord to giue vs his good ſpirit of prayer: which if we will doe, no doubt wee ſhall find his promiſe to be true, that then The ſpirit of God in vs ſhall<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15176:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> make requeſt for vs. For as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt comforteth his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in an other caſe,<note place="margin">Math. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſeeing that they ſhould bee brought before the Gouernours and Kings for his ſake: But when they deliuer you vp, take no thought how, or what you ſhall ſpeake, for it ſhal be giuen you in that houre, what you ſhall ſay; for it is not you that ſpeake, but the ſpirit of your Father that ſpeaketh in you: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo wee ſhall finde by experience, that when we are moſt vnfit to pray, if we will not yeeld to this infirmitie and ſlothfulneſſe, but ſtriue againſt it, there ſhall be a ſecret inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in vs, whereby we ſhall bee ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to doe ſomething; and there ſhall be a labour of the heart, and an endeauour of the minde, aſpiring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which we may ſeeme not to attaine vnto: and there ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſighings, though few words; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great deſires, though fewe voices:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15176:22"/> yea, there ſhall bee that which wee cannot greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue of our ſelues, and euery thing ſhall be vnſpeakable: according to the ſaying of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, That when we know not what to pray as we ought, the ſpirit of God ſhall make requeſt for vs, with ſighes which cannot be expreſſed.</p>
            <p>For no doubt theſe men that we ſpake of before, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> euen at thoſe times, when they could not tell what and how to pray of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; yet the Spirit of God helping their infirmities, they did pray in ſome good acceptable manner, and there were at the leaſt vnſpeakeable ſighs and groanes ſtirred vp in them: for it is ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. king. 20.3.</note> that he then turned his face to the wall, and praied to the Lord: and afterwards it is ſaid, The Lord did heare his prayer. And <hi>Dauid,</hi> when as in his owne feeling he did but roare and ſigh, and mourne; as he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.6.</note> I goe mourning all the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15176:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> day, I roare for the griefe of mine heart: yet then hee made his deſires knowne vnto the Lord in prayer, and poured them our very plentifully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. And when hee did but mourne and make a noiſe, he deſireth the Lord to hearken vnto him,<note place="margin">and 55.2.</note> and to anſwer him: and when he ſaith, that his groanings were like the Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, and the ſparrows, &amp; the ſhrike owles, yet to ſhew, that in them there was a worke of Gods ſpirit, which made them acceptable to God, hee beginneth the Pſalme thus: O Lord,<note place="margin">and 102.1.</note> heare my praier, &amp; let my crie come vnto thee: incline thine eares vnto me, when I call make haſt to heare me. And to ſhew that his example in thus praying was for the inſtruction and comfort of the Church, it is thus intituled, A praier of the afflicted, when he ſhal be in diſtreſſe, &amp; powre out his meditation before the Lord: Shewing not onely that the afflicted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15176:23"/> in their diſtreſſe doe thus pray, but that the Lord heareth them therein, and graunteth their deſire.</p>
            <p>And thus is it ſaide of the whole Church of God in Egypt, at what time,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.14.</note> as they were greatly oppreſſed, ſo that they grewe wearie of their liues, by ſore labour in clay, and in bricke, and in all worke in the fielde, with all manner of bondage, which was laid vpon them moſt cruelly; ſo there was great ignorance and much weakeneſſe among them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not knowing well many of them how to pray to God,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.23</note> They ſighed to God for the bondage, and cried; and their crie for the bondage came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and he heard their moane, and looked vpon them, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto them: and hee ſaid vnto Moſes,<note place="margin">&amp; 3.7.</note> I haue ſurely ſeene the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my people, and haue heard their crie, for I know their ſorrowes, therfore I am come down to deliuer them.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15176:23"/>
            <p>This is then a moſt notable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in all afflictions, that wee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in Chriſt, and made thereby partakers of his holy ſpirit, it ſhall ſo helpe vs in all our infirmities, that when we cannot tell what, or how to pray as we ought, it ſhall teach vs ſo to doe it, as wee may haue hope and comfort of beeing heard. For this is that which <hi>Paul</hi> addeth in the next verſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.27.</note> That hee that ſearcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the meaning of the Spirit; for he maketh requeſt for the Saints according to the will of God. Where by knowing, he doth not onely meane that he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it, as hee doth all other things; but he accepteth and alloweth of it, and doth moſt willingly graunt ſuch requeſts, as though they were made in farre better liking to our ſelues: &amp; ſo is the word taken in the firſt Pſalme, where the Prophet ſaith, The Lord knoweth the way of the<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.6.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15176:24"/> righteous, that is, hee doth make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them, approoue, and allowe of them, regard and proſper them.</p>
            <p>For as wee haue ſeene euen now, hee heard the crie of the Iſraelites, when they did but ſigh &amp; make their moane, and did deliuer them from their cruell bondage; &amp; he did heare king <hi>Hezekiah</hi> chattering in his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er like a Crane, and raiſed him vp from death, and added fifteen yeares more vnto his life;<note place="margin">2. Ki. 20.11</note> and to confirme him therein, hee brought againe the ſhadow tenne degrees backe, by the degrees whereby it had gone downe in the diall of <hi>Ahaz.</hi> And hee heard <hi>Dauid</hi> when he roared for the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his paine, and forgaue the puniſhment of his ſinne; that is, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue him his ſinne, and remooued the puniſhment thereof. And wee may remember our ſelues, if we haue marked any thing, how the Lord hath heard vs many times in our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15176:24"/> greateſt need, when we haue howled and cried, rather then made any ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and well ordered prayer: yea, when we haue rather moaned then ſpoken, rather ſighed then vttered a word. For the Lord in this caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not ſo much the multitude of wordes, as he looketh to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his ſpirit, and granteth that, though they ſpeake neuer a word.</p>
            <p>For euen as a father or mother hauing a young infant ſicke of ſome ſore diſeaſe, though the childe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake and call for this and that, yet they are readie to helpe it; and if it be elder, and can ſpeake, yet being full of paine, it cannot call for things as it ought: neuertheleſſe, if they can by any ſignes gueſſe at the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, they will accept as much of it, as though the childe had ſpoken very diſtinctly, and vſed many words: Euen ſo the Lord, who is infinitely filled with the bowels of compaſſion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15176:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> towards vs in Chriſt, farre aboue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny father or mother; inſomuch as the Lord ſaith, Can a woman forget her childe,<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.15.</note> and not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? though they ſhould forget, yet will not I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thee: though hee delighteth to heare vs pray to him, as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth to his Church, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, My doue, ſhew me thy ſight, let me heare thy voice;<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> for thy voice is ſweete, and thy ſight comely: yet when by the extremities of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries wee are ſo oppreſſed or diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that wee cannot in any orderly manner pray vnto him as we ought; yet he alloweth of the ſighes &amp; ſobs that we offer vp vnto him, and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſo much our wordes (which ſometimes none or very fewe) as the meaning of his ſpirit, which is large and plentifull in vs.</p>
            <p>And hereupon it commeth to paſſe, that the Lord in his iuſt mercie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15176:25"/> imputeth not vnto his ſeruants the manifold rebellions of their fleſh, or great complaints in their praier; as hee did not vnto <hi>Iob</hi> nor to <hi>Dauid,</hi> who were full of them, as wee haue ſeene before; becauſe he hath reſpect vnto the meaning of his ſpirit in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: As the mother is not ſo much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or offended with the murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, impatiencie, and froward out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries of her poore ſicke childe; as ſhe by the leaſt token gueſſeth at the meaning of him, and taketh that in good part, and giueth to him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay to theſe things? Is it true indeede, that the Lord will vouchſafe to looke vpon the low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of his ſeruants; and haue reſpect vnto poore ſinnefull creatures, who when they are fallen into the bottom of their iuſt deſerued miſerie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then can not pray vnto him one word aright; and when they begin
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15176:26"/> to ſpeake vnto him, euen then their tongue cleaueth to the roofe of their mouth; that he will yet heare their ſighs, and their cries? yea vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he that of his great mercie will beare with ſuch great weakneſſe in men,<note place="margin">Matt. 12.20.</note> that he will not breake a bruiſed reede, nor quench the ſmoking flaxe; he will of the like mercie heare, not onely the well ordered prayers of his Church, but euen the very cryings &amp; roarings of his ſeruants, though they be like the Pellicans and the owles: yea their mournings, though they be like to the doues: yea, when they ſay nothing, neither indeed can, their very ſobs and ſighs, which come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the abundance of a troubled ſpirit, and can not be expreſſed: for he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of the meaning of his Spirit, which worketh theſe things in them: and if they could, thereby they are willing to performe better ſeruice vnto him, and are ſorie that they can
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15176:26"/> not doe it. What can be more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vnto vs, then this?</p>
            <p>Therefore in all our neceſſities let vs goe vnto the Lord in Chriſt with great boldneſſe, and come vnto the throne of grace: and though we can not vtter many wordes, yet let vs ſpeake vnto him: for ſurely the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our praiers conſiſteth not in the multitude or well placing of our words, but in the requeſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of our hearts: and therefore if we can pray but two or three words, &amp; ſay with the poore Publican, Lord,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> be merciful vnto me a ſinner; or with the Apoſtles, Lord increaſe our faith;<note place="margin">&amp; 17.5.</note> or with the man in the Goſpel, Lord I beleeue, Lord help mine vnbeleef;<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> or with the blind man,<note place="margin">Matt. 9.29.</note> O ſon of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid haue mercy vpon me; or with the theefe vpon the croſſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Lord remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me in thy kingdome, &amp;c. this ſhort prayer proceeding from the Spirit of God in vs, and offered vp in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15176:27"/> the mediation of Chriſt Ieſus, and in the vertue of his prayers, ſhall be as well receiued of him, when we can doe no better, as if we had ſpent an whole houre in prayer.</p>
            <p>Yea, if we do but lift vp our minds vnto God, and pray in our ſpirite, though we vtter not one word, as that godly woman <hi>Hannah</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Samuel</hi> did;<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.10</note> who beeing troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in her minde praied vnto the Lord, and wept ſore: but how did ſhee pray? ſhee ſpake in her heart, her lips did mooue onely, but her voice was not heard: The Lord will heare vs, as he did her, and giue her accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her deſire: as ſhee afterward confeſſed to <hi>Heli</hi> the Prieſt: I praied for this child, and the Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me my deſire, which I asked of him. And ſo did <hi>Nehemiah</hi> pray vnto God, for he waiting vpon the King of Babylon as hee ſate at table, and beeing ſad in his preſence more then
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15176:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> he had wont to be, the King deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him the cauſe, &amp; he told him: then hauing leaue of the King to ask what he would for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his deſire; it is ſaide that hee praied to the God of heauen: that is,<note place="margin">Nehe. 2.4.</note> he lifted vp his mind vnto God, and deſired him to bleſſe him in that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe of his, and ſo he did. So we if either we can not pray in words, or waite opportunity of time and place, and doe but ſigh vnto him after an vnſpeakeable manner, the Lord will not refuſe that, becauſe it proceedeth from his Spirit.</p>
            <p>And as this may be no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto vs in our affliction, ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the next verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing doth for our further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhew what is the ende of all the afflictions of the children of God; namely, their benefit and good, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Alſo we know that al things worke together for the beſt to them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15176:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> that loue God, euen to them that are called of his purpoſe. In which words he miniſtreth this ſoueraigne medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine againſt the contagion &amp; poiſon of all affliction, telling vs, that they come to the beleeuers not for their hurt, but for their ſingular good; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing they befall them not by fortune or chance, but by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall prouidence of God, and that for the ſame ende: who as he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen them from euerlaſting, ſo in the ſame counſell of his he ordained that they ſhould in their croſſes bee like vnto his ſonne.<note place="margin">Verſ. 29.</note> For thoſe whom hee knew before, hee alſo predeſtinate to be made like to the image of his ſon, that he might bee the firſt borne of many brethren: and therefore hee calleth them in time, iuſtifieth them by faith, and by the croſſe bringeth them to eternall glorie, as he did his owne naturall ſonne: as it is ſaid in the next words,<note place="margin">30.</note> Moreouer, whom he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15176:28"/> predeſtinated, them alſo he called; &amp; whome he called, them alſo he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and whome he iuſtified, them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he glorified.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he boldly concludeth, that no affliction ſhall be able to hurt them, ſeeing that the Lord is with them in the ſame, meaning thereby to doe them good: for he ſpeaketh after a moſt confident maner, What ſhall we then ſay to theſe things?<note place="margin">31.</note> If God be on our ſide, who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs? as if he had ſaid, ſeeing that God is with vs in all our afflictions by his prouidence and power, and by the aſſiſtance of his holy Spirit, none of them ſhall be able to doe vs any harme: And the truth of Gods loue and meaning towards vs this way, he confirmeth by a moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proof, when he addeth,<note place="margin">32.</note> Who ſpared not his owne Sonne, but gaue him for vs all to death, how ſhall he not with him giue vs all things alſo? In which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15176:29"/> words he ſheweth, that we haue no cauſe to feare, no not in any croſſe, that the Lord will not giue vs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is profitable for vs, ſeeing that he hath not ſpared his owne Sonne to ſaue vs.</p>
            <p>Therfore when he ſaith, All things worke together for the beſt to them that feare God, it is moſt true, whether we take it generally, as the words may be expounded, namely, not onely proſperitie but aduerſitie alſo, not onely health but ſicknes, not onely libertie but impriſonment, not onely honour but diſhonour; make for the beſt to thoſe that loue God. Or whether it be reſtrained to this particular purpoſe of his; namely, to affliction of what nature or kind ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. It is no doubt the intent of the Apoſtle to ſpeake of this latter, and to ſhew, that all afflictions doe not onely not hinder the ſaluation of the godly, but doe greatly further the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15176:29"/> ſame. Which ſaying of his, though it containeth an whole and entire mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by it ſelfe, yet beeing inferred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former wordes, he ſeemeth therein to anſwer a ſecret obiection, which might ariſe in mens mindes from thence; namely, that it ſeemeth many times that the Lord doth not heare the praiers of the afflicted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their afflictions be not onely not remooued, according to their praiers, but ſomtimes increaſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their earneſt deſire.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee muſt remember, what hath beene alreadie ſaid touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter, namly, how the Lord in graunting our requeſts, looketh not ſo much to the particular things which we deſire, as to the meaning of his Spirit in vs: and granteth that, in turning our afflictions to our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good: wheras if they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently remooued, the Lord ſeeth that it would be far worſe with vs, though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15176:30"/> we imagine the contrarie. For as if one in a burning feauer ſhould in the middeſt of his fit impatiently deſire to be waſhed with colde water; and then the skilfull Phyſitian ſtanding by, beeing his friend alſo ſhould giue him ſome wholeſome conſerues or other cooling thing, hee ſhould in denying that particular thing dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, graunt vnto his generall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which was, that he might haue ſome thing giuen him, that might do him moſt good, though now beeing diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered, he was not able to iudge of it, but did miſtake one thing for an other, and thought that to be beſt, as to be plunged into the colde water, which indeede is the worſt: So wee whatſoeuer we aske in our diſtreſſe by praier vnto God, our meaning is and muſt be, if it be ruled by Gods ſpirit, that we would haue that giuen vnto vs, which might procure our beſt good, and further our ſaluation
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15176:30"/> moſt of all. Therefore if the Lord ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our croſſes to remaine, and turne them to our good, though we in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular praied for the cleane taking of them away, hee fulfilleth both theſe promiſes vnto vs at once; namely, he giueth vs according to the meaſure of his ſpirit in vs; and hee alſo cauſeth them to worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God.</p>
            <p>Thus then <hi>Paul</hi> beſought the Lord thrice, that is, very often,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.8.</note> that the meſſenger of Satan might depart from him; and yet the Lord ſuffered him ſtil to buffet the Apoſtle, leaſt he ſhould bee exalted out of meaſure, through the aboundance of reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were giuen vnto him: and the Lord gaue him this further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that his grace ſhould be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him to vphold and ſtrengthen him, and that the power of God ſhould be ſeen in the Apoſtles weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Lord in denying this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15176:31"/> of his, did giue him according to the meaning of his ſpirit in him, which was, that the Lord would deale with him this way, as it ſhould make moſt for his owne glorie, and for the furtherance of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaluation; and alſo did cauſe this affliction to worke together with other things for his beſt good; for this did him more good remaining, then if it had beene taken away: for hereby he had more experience of his owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of the power of God, then otherwiſe he could haue had.</p>
            <p>And thus alſo the Lord hath veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from time to time vnto the reſt of his ſeruants the truth of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his, which is vttered by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10.24.</note> God will fulfill the deſire of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that is, God will not onely bleſſe thoſe that ſerue him, but hee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe thoſe bleſſings vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt of all, which they eſpecially deſire,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15176:31"/> and do moſt earneſtly pray vnto him for: according to that that is ſaid in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.19.</note> Hee will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him. Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are ſo to bee vnderſtood, not that he will alwaies giue them euery particular thing that they aske, for many times through ignorance, or beeing diſtempered with ſome te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, they aske that that is hurtfull, and then God denieth them: but he giueth them ſome other thing that is more profitable for them, according to the generall meaning of the ſpirit of God in them. And ſo doe parents vnto their little children, whom they loue full dearely, when they aske kniues and ſuch hurtfull things, in ſtead of them, they in wiſedome giue them ſome other thing that they ſhall delight in as much; and ſo ſtill their frowardneſſe, and giue them their deſire in another kind.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo the Lord fulfilleth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15176:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> of his ſeruants, by making an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, when as they name one thing, and he giueth them an other as good, or better: as it is ſaide in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.4.</note> He asked life of thee, &amp; thou gaueſt him a long life, euen for euer and euer: where in the perſon of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid he ſheweth how God dealeth with his Church, they aske life of him, and he giueth not onely that, but eternall life: as he did to <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah;</hi> but yet ſometimes they that are weake and ſicke, and deſire life, they haue it not graunted, but linger and pine away euen vnto death, and ſo God taketh them into his bleſſed kingdome, and giues them eternall life, which is better then that life that they deſired. And thus did he deale with many of the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did by death iudge and chaſtiſe in this world, that they might be ſaued in the world to come.</p>
            <p>And this was the caſe of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15176:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeruant <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 3.25.</note> who in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe deſired earneſtly of the Lord, that he might goe ouer and ſee that good land that was beyond Iorden, and that goodly mountain Sion, and Lebanon: but he would not heare him in that, and ſo cauſed him to goe vp into mount Nebo,<note place="margin">chap. 34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vnto the top of Piſgah where he ſhewed him all the land, and there he died, and ſo entred into the kingdome of heauen, and tooke poſſeſſion of it for euer, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this land was but a type &amp; figure: and ſo the Lord denying him that particular, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come into the land of Canaan, gaue him that that was farre better, &amp; whereby he was more confirmed in the ſame of God, and in the truth of his couenant; euen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of heauen, and ſo gaue him according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>But further touching this matter, we are more generally to vnderſtand,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15176:33"/> that the Apoſtle ſaith not onely, that the croſſe ſhall turne to our good, but that this ſhall be verified of all the croſſes that euery way come vpon vs, be they neuer ſo ſtrange, or vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for: whether it be ſicknes, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, impriſonment, baniſhment, loſſe of husband, wife, children, father and mother, friends and kinred, loſſe of name and credit, or any thing els: as ſorrow and griefe of minde, and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſpirit. Which is wiſely to be marked of vs, leaſt at any time we might be deceiued, to think when the Lord ſhall lay his hand vpon vs, as it pleaſeth him, that if it were ſome other affliction, then that which now is come vpon vs, we could haue ſome good hope in it; but this is ſo great, it toucheth vs ſo nearely, that we can not poſſibly ſee, how or which way it ſhould bring vs any good.</p>
            <p>And as the Deuill is readie to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault vs with this temptation, ſo we by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15176:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> reaſon of our corruption are too prone to yeild vnto his perſwaſion therein, and ſo by impatiencie to be wearie of the croſſe, as not able to looke for any good from it. We ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that wee might comfortably withſtand this temptation of his, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that we muſt holde our ſelues faſt to the words of the Apoſtle, who ſaith, that all things worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God;<note place="margin">Gal. 1.9.</note> he ſpeaketh of all, not of this or that: againſt which if any, yea an Angel from heauen ſhould perſwade vs, we muſt hold him accurſed. We muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that this good commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all affliction, not as though it were naturall &amp; proper vnto it: for indeed it is otherwiſe, that of it ſelfe it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men worſe, as the ſunne harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the clay: and it driueth men from good, as the rodde driueth the child away from the mother. And this is that which Satan aimeth at in all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15176:34"/> men,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.11.</note> as hee did in righteous <hi>Iob,</hi> though he preuailed not, when hee ſaid of him to the Lord, Stretch out thine hand, &amp; touch all that he hath, and ſee if he will not blaſpheme thee to thy face. And thus he preuaileth with the wicked in all croſſes that come vpon them, as wee ſee in the example of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> king of Egypt, who by the ten plagues that God ſent vpon him, was made more hard hearted, and waxed ſtill worſe and worſe, and would not heare the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, to let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael goe.</p>
            <p>But with the children of God it is not ſo, the goodneſſe of God towards them ouercommeth the malice of the deuill againſt them. And as in the wilderneſſe the ſting of the fierie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were healed in the bodies of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by looking vp to the braſen ſerpent;<note place="margin">Num. 21.8.</note> ſo the venime and poiſon of all croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is taken away in the children of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15176:34"/> God, by vertue of the croſſe of Chriſt; ſo that contrarie to the nature of it, it worketh good: as alſo by the death of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55.</note> the ſting of death is taken away, ſo that it cannot hurt any of his, but doth them the greateſt good, beeing thereby made for them a paſſage into eternal life. The which that it might not ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs, much leſſe impoſſible; namly, that afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurtfull in it ſelfe to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſhould work for the beſt to thoſe that loue God: wee muſt remember that euen men by their wiſdome are able to make thoſe things ſerue for the benefit of man, which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are moſt hurtfull vnto him.</p>
            <p>For the Phyſition through his skill can cure a man by Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and bleſſing, and ſo make him ſtronger then hee was before, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away ſome part of his blood, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that wherein the life conſiſteth; and by taking away other humors, &amp;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15176:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo diminiſhing a great part of his fleſh: and the Chyrurgion by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and piercing the fleſh with an hotte yron, or eating it away with ſome corraſiues, is able by theſe woundes and hurtfull things, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſtate of the members of the bodie: Then the Lord much more by that which in it ſelfe would hurt our ſoules, is able to cure them; and to doe them good. And if the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie can ſo temper that which in it owne nature is poyſon (as the Vipers fleſh) ſo temper it I ſay, with other wholeſome ingredients, and correct it with thoſe that be cordiall; that of it hee will make a moſt ſoueraigne Treacle, and ſuch an wholeſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as ſhall expell poyſon, and driue it from the heart; and ſo make that which of it ſelfe would cauſe death, to bee a ſpeciall preſeruer of life: Shall not the Lord by his infinite wiſedome, goodneſſe, and almightie
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15176:35"/> power, the Lord I ſay,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note> which cauſed the light to ſhine out of darkeneſſe, contrarie to the nature of it, and who calleth the things that bee not, as though they were, and ſo cauſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be, and which bringeth good out of euill, euen his owne glorie out of the ſin of man; ſhall not he bee much more able by the moſt grieuous croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that can befall vs, to worke the greateſt good for vs that may be?</p>
            <p>Therefore when we would looke for good from our afflictions, and ſo be comforted in them, patiently bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, in hope of the bleſſed fruit that we ſhall reape by them; wee muſt not ſo much looke to the things themſelues, how fit they bee for vs, nor to our ſelues, how wee bee fitted for them; as to the truth of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made vnto vs concerning this matter, &amp; ſo be ſure that the Lord wil worke our good thereby, becauſe he that is true and al-ſufficient hath ſaid
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15176:36"/> ſaid it. And this one perſwaſion no doubt, ſhould worke in vs great pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in all our afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; yea it ſhould make vs cheerefully, and with our heads lifted vp, &amp; not hanging down, to beare them; for how many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous things will naturall men indure willingly, if they ſee that they will make for the bettering of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate? As what will not the ſicke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuffer at the hands of the Phyſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Chirurgion by launcing, purging, fearing, diet, &amp;c. when he is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that they will procure his bodily health? ſhould not a Chriſtian man and woman much more indure hard things at the hands of God, ſeeing he hath ſaid that they ſhall procure the health of his ſoule, &amp; worke his good that way.</p>
            <p>But indeede herein lieth the point of this matter, and this is all in all, namely, that the poore afflicted ſoule knoweth not, that the Lord by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15176:36"/> his affliction will work his good: and that maketh him ſo vnquiet, and euer complaining: for giue him this faith, and the feeling of it, that his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be turned vnto his good, and lay vpon him whatſoeuer you will, he is content to beare it. Therefore for the ſatisfying of our ſelues here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, let vs hearken to that which the Apoſtle ſaith, Wee know,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> that all things worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God: which is as if he had ſaide, though you becauſe of your ignorance, vnbeleefe, and want of experience, are vncerten what wil be the happie iſſue of all your affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, yet we know very well, that all ſhall worke together for our &amp; your good. Which he ſpeaketh confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both as a teacher of the Church, an Apoſtle, and as a man of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and therefore we ought to giue credit vnto him, rather then to our ſelues. Euen as the patient doth to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15176:37"/> the Phyſitian, though himſelfe had neuer experience of any ſuch thing before: when he ſaith vnto him, I knowe that this will make for the health of your bodie, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of your life.</p>
            <p>And in this thing wee ought to giue credit vnto the Apoſtle ſo much the more, becauſe vnto his own word and ſaying, he ioyneth the teſtimony of many other, ſaying, Wee know, meaning the reſt of the Apoſtles and miniſters, and men of experience; he ſaith, that all of them knew it, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this word beeing confirmed by the mouthes not of two or three witneſſes onely, but hauing (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) ſo great a cloud of witneſſes for it,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 12.1.</note> it ſhould be receiued without all gaineſaying. For it is all one, as if the ſicke patient fearing to take the potion that is preſcribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, leſt it ſhould make him more ſicke, he ſhould haue not onely one,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15176:37"/> but an whole counſell of Phyſitians ſaying vnto him, that vndoubtedly this medicine is like to do you good; we know the working of it very wel, and haue had great experience of it in many, you neede not to feare it, take it vpon our credit. This would much mooue and incourage him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
            <p>So no doubt this ſhould correct the too much feare that is in vs, of beeing hurt by the croſſe, when we heare ſo many excellent and famous men, very skilfull therein, to ſpeake ſo boldly vnto vs of the benefit of it: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe, whome ſeeing that we are moſt readie to beleeue in all other things, why ſhould we not giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vnto them in this alſo? But that we might doe it the rather, let vs a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſider in particular of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the croſſe. And though the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle name one great one here, which might be ſufficient; yet before
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15176:38"/> we come to it, let vs ſee, what other endes of it the Scripture affoardeth vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, we ſhall finde it to be a ſpeciall meanes to draw vs from the too much loue of this world; that according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.31.</note> they that vſe this world might be as though they vſed it not, that is, that we might be ſo addicted to theſe worldly things, that we ſet not our affections too much vpon them. For ſuch is the corruption of our nature, that when wee haue all things at will, we are ſo wedded to this world, that we thinke it beſt for vs alwaies to abide here, and here we would ſet vp our tabernacles for euer; and wee are readie to ſay with the worldling in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> Soule, thou haſt much goods laid vp for many yeares, liue at eaſe, eate and drinke, &amp; take thy pleaſure: and though hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be a thouſand times heauenly,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15176:38"/> yet we deſire it not at all, or not ſo earneſtly as we ſhould; but wee are ſtill earthly minded, and as it were groueling vpon the earth: ſo hardly or not at all can wee come vnto that that we are exhorted vnto, to ſeeke,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to ſet our affections on thoſe things that are aboue, and not on things which are in the earth; yet when by affliction we ſhal finde that there is no contentation in any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate here below, it may mooue vs to deſpiſe all worldly things, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire vnto heauen,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> where in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God is the fulneſſe of ioy, &amp; at his right hand are pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe the holy Patriarkes ſuffered ſo many afflictions in the daies of their pilgrimages, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in their ſeueral ſtories; in reſpect of which one of them ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That his daies were fewe and euill. For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many earthly things were promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15176:39"/> vnto them, yet that they might not ſtaie in them, but from them, as it were by certaine ſtairs, they might aſcend vnto the conſideration of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, which the earthly did ſhadow out vnto them, and which they were eſpecially to looke for; he mingled his manifold great bleſſings with manifold croſſes: &amp; in that land that was promiſed vnto them, they had no certaine abiding, that they might ſeeke after the kingdome of heauen: As the Apoſtle ſaith vnto the Hebrewes,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 11.9.</note> By faith <hi>Abraham</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in the land of promiſe, as in a ſtrange countrey, as one that dwelt in tents, with <hi>Izaack</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> heires with him of the ſame promiſe; for he looked for a citie hauing a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe builder and maker is God. Theſe men had none inheritance in the land of Canaan, that they might not dream of a perpetuitie there, but might thinke of heauen, as of a better
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15176:39"/> countrey, where they ſhould remain for euer, confeſſing themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to bee but ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes on the earth.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo the Lord dealeth with many before their death, laying long and grieuous diſeaſes vpon them, as he did vpon his ſeruant <hi>Iob,</hi> that they finding no reſt in this world, might be willing to goe out of it when hee ſhall ſend for them, and ſay with olde father <hi>Simeon,</hi> Lord,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace: yea that they might deſire death moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, which before as moſt ougly and loathſome they did abhorre: and ſo ſaie with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> I deſire to bee looſed, and to be with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> which is beſt of all. So that as the mother by ſome vnpleaſant thing weaneth the ſucking childe from the breaſt, now when ſtronger meate is more fit for it, vpon which otherwiſe it would alwaies linger to the hurt of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15176:40"/> it; ſo the Lord by the croſſe weaneth our affections from the profits and pleaſures of the world, and ſo turneth it vnto our good: and therefore if by experience we find that by any affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we growe more wearie of the world, or leſſe in loue with it, we are not onely to take it patiently, but therein ſee the truth of this promiſe: we know that all things worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the beſt to thoſe that loue God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer by affliction the Lord bringeth vs to a more thorough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and ſorrow for our ſinnes, and worketh that in vs therby, which the word did not before; when wee finde by woefull experience what great miſeries our ſins haue brought vs vnto, and how iuſt and true God is in all his threatnings.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11 31</note> For if when we haue ſinned, we would iudge our ſelues before hand, God would not iudge vs: but when wee are iudged,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15176:40"/> wee are chaſtened of the Lord, that we might not bee condemned with the world: whereunto agreeth the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, which is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to bee true by daily experience; that whether the Lord laie vpon men ſickeneſſe, or impriſonment, or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and want, or baniſhment, or ſuch like;<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.11.</note> when he hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth the heart with heauineſſe they crie vnto the Lord in their trouble: ſo that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bringeth men to humilitie for their ſinnes, and to pray vnto God to be pardoned, and to be deliuered. As we ſee in the example of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall childe, who by great miſerie came to repent him of his riotous life; for when he had ſpent all,<note place="margin">Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a great famine in that land, and he began to bee in neceſſitie, which afterwards was ſo great, that hee would faine haue filled his bellie with the huskes that the ſwine ate, but no man gaue them him: then he
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15176:41"/> ſaid, I will riſe and goe to my father, and ſay vnto him, Father, I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt heauen, and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne, make me as one of thy hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſeruants. Thus wee ſee by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto what meaſure of humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and repentance for his ſinnes, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of them he was brought vnto: a moſt excellent fruit of the croſſe.</p>
            <p>The like may bee ſaid of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who after that they had ſold him into Egypt, and made their father beleeue that hee was torne in pieces of ſome wilde beaſt; though we may preſume of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they beeing brought vp, and ſtill li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the houſe of their godly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iacob,</hi> they did ſecretly repent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ill dealing towards their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> yet many yeares after, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen twentie or thereabout, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were in aduerſitie, the memorie of it renued it ſelfe afreſh, and thereby
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15176:41"/> they were brought more ſeriouſly to iudge themſelues for it; for they ſaid one to another,<note place="margin">Gen. 42.21</note> We haue verily ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt our brother, in that wee ſawe the anguiſh of his ſoule when he beſought vs, and wee would not heare him, therefore is this trouble come vpon vs. Thus this croſſe was turned to their good, in that it brought them to a further ſight and feeling of their ſinne, and to a more voluntarie and free confeſſion of the ſame.</p>
            <p>So that affliction in this reſpect is compared to fire that purgeth the gold, and conſumeth the droſſe of it; and vnto a file that ſcowreth off the ruſt of yron, and maketh it bright; &amp; vnto a purgation, that expelleth the corrupt and ſuperfluous humors out of the bodie. Therefore euen as the fire doth not hurt the gold in conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the droſſe, neither the file hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the yron in taking away the ruſt,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15176:42"/> neither doth the purgation hurt the bodie in expelling of ill humors: So afflictions cauſing vs to abhorre and leaue ſome ſinne or other, which if we continued in, would deſtroy vs, may truely be ſaid not to hurt vs, but to worke our good, of what nature or kinde ſoeuer they bee: according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, All things worke together for the good of thoſe that loue God.</p>
            <p>In the third place, this is the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of affliction, that it preſerueth vs from many ſinnes, which otherwiſe through our owne corruption, and the temptations of the world and Satan we might fall into; but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God, as it were vnder the rodde, we are thereby kept in more awe: So that as Phyſicke ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not only to cure vs of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which we are alreadie fallen into, but alſo and eſpecially to preuent them, and to keepe vs in ſome tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15176:42"/> eſtate of health: So the croſſe recouereth vs out of ſinne, when we are fallen into it, and preſerueth vs from many, which otherwiſe might creepe vpon vs. And therefore as ſome ſickly bodies are driuen to diet themſelues, and are in a continuall courſe of phyſicke, to preuent that which their corrupt eſtate would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe neceſſarily pull vpon them: So others by reaſon of the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their ſoules, and the manifold offences that they liue amongſt, are alwaies, or the greateſt part of their liues in the diet of affliction, as it were the phyſicke of their ſoules: not ſo much to bring them from groſſe and grieuous ſinnes, which they are as yet free from; as to keepe them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling into them, which the Lord foreſeeth they are moſt readie to do, in reſpect of their ages, callings, and places, that they liue in.</p>
            <p>If then the Lord at any time deale
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15176:43"/> with vs, as men do with vnruly co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, or vntamed heyfers, which are kept from ſtraying out of their paſtures with hedges and ditches, ſo that they can not break out without their own hurt: ſo the Lord puts thornes and bryars as it were in our waies, that is, laieth affliction vpon vs, and ſo ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the way againſt vs, that wee might not breake forth by any kinde of diſobedience either on the right hand, or on the left, to our own hurt muſt we not needs ſay, that euen this way, as well as any other, the Lord worketh by affliction our ſingular good? And this is that, which God promiſed to his owne people among the idolatrous Iſraelites, namely, that by his afflictions he would ſo keepe them in, and bring them to ſuch ſtraitnes, that they ſhold haue no luſt to play the wantons, and to fall away from him by idolatrie after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others: when he faith, I will
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15176:43"/> ſtoppe thy way with thornes,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.6.</note> and make an hedge, that ſhee ſhall not finde her paths. So that their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be an hedge of ſharpe thornes to pricke them, leaſt they ſhould breake out, and ſtray fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods commandements.</p>
            <p>And this as it is a ſingular ende of affliction, ſo Dauid pronounceth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſſed that are partakers of it to that ende, and can make that good vſe of it to themſelues, ſaying, Bleſſed is the man, whome thou chaſtiſeſt, O Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.12.</note> and teacheſt in thy law: that thou maieſt giue him reſt from the daies of euill, whiles the pit is digged for the wicked. So that it is a bleſſed thing to be ſo corrected, that he is taught the right vſe of it, euen to walke more carefully in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods law, that ſo he may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape thoſe puniſhments which ſhall come vpon the wicked for their ſinns to their deſtruction. And this vſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15176:44"/> made of his affliction, as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">&amp; 116.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> before I was affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, I went aſtray, but now I keepe thy words: ſo that by his affliction he was kept from going aſtray, as he had wont to doe, and was conſtrained in a reuerent feare to walke in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of Gods holy law: whereupon he concludeth thus by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience:<note place="margin">71.</note> It is good for me that I haue beene afflicted, that I may feare thy ſtatutes. Thus affliction was a ſenſible kind of teaching to cauſe him to liue after Gods ſtatutes, and not after the common courſe of the world.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, afflictions in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are called trialls, becauſe that by them the Lord trieth vs, and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth what is in vs: not that he is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it; for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith vnto God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139 2.</note> Thou knoweſt my ſitting &amp; ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, thou vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt my thoughts a farre off; thou compaſſeſt my paths,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15176:44"/> and my lying downe, and art accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to all my waies: for there is not a word in my tongue, but loe thou knoweſt it, O Lord. So that he hath full &amp; perfect knowledge of vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any triall: yet he trieth vs by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, becauſe thereby he would haue our ſelues and others through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to know, what is in vs, and in what meaſure: and that both in reſpect of the good and euill that is in vs; which without the triall could not ſo well be knowne. Which kind of triall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to this ende, that if we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued any good grace, we might be thankefull to God for it, and for the meaſure of it: if not, we might labor for it; and if we haue any ſinne in vs, we might repent and ſtriue againſt it: if not, we might take heede, that wee fall not into it for the time to come; and ſo euery way God might be glorified.</p>
            <p>And thus ſpeaketh the Apoſtle S.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15176:45"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> of the afflictions of the church, comparing them vnto fire, whereby mettalls are tried, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, Now for a ſeaſon (if neede require) ye are in heauines,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.6.</note> through manifold tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that the triall of your faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much more pretious then gold that periſheth (thogh it be tried with fire) might be found vnto your praiſe, and honour, and glorie at the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Ieſus Chriſt. Where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, that if men by the fire will trie their gold, to that ende, that they might certenly know, what is the value of it, and yet it is but a thing that periſheth, and therefore in no wiſe to be compared to faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt excellent graces of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: Then the Lord much more may make triall of them by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, to the ende that all men may ſee them to be ſo pretious, and ſo pure as they be; and that they may be diſcerned from the hypocriticall and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15176:45"/> counterfeit ſhewes of vertue that are in the wicked and vngodly: that ſo men might make ſure reckoning of the one, and not truſt to the other, &amp; ſo be deceiued by them.</p>
            <p>Thus it is truly ſaid, that God did prooue <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.1.</note> when he ſaide vnto him, Take thine onely ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> whome thou loueſt, and get thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of Moriah, and offer him there for a burnt offering vpon one of the mountaines, which I wil ſhew thee: and he did ſo: and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that by faith he offered vp Iſaac, when he was tried:<note place="margin">Heb. 11.17.</note> ſo that this was a great triall vnto him, to ſacrifice his owne ſonne, whome he ſo loued, and in whome he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the promiſe. But when he ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forth his hand,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.10.</note> and tooke the knife to kill his ſonne, the Lord ſaid vnto him from heauen, Lay not thine hand vpon the child, neither doe any thing vnto him: for now I know, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15176:46"/> thou feareſt God, ſeeing for my ſake, thou haſt not ſpared thine onely ſon. The Lord knew the obedience of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham before, but he ſpeaketh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mens vnderſtanding, that now he by good proofe and triall knew it, and made it knowne to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham himſelfe, and to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>And thus our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpel by a parable ſheweth, how it is knowne, who haue receiued the ſeede of Gods word into good hearts, and who into bad: namely, they that continue in the obedience of it in the time of temptation and triall, and they that fall away, ſaying, They that are on the ſtones,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.13.</note> are they, which when they haue heard, receiue the word with ioy; but they haue no rootes: which for a while beleeue, but in the time of temptation goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Thus though they ſeemed to beleeue for a time, yet when they fall
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15176:46"/> away in temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by this triall it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that the word of God was neuer throughly rooted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And by an other compariſon alſo he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, how vpon triall it is manifeſt, who are profitable hearers of the word of God, and who are not: for he that heareth the word of God,<note place="margin">Math 7.24.</note> &amp; doth it, is like a wiſe man, which hath builded his houſe on a rocke; and the raine fell, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beate vpon that houſe, and it fell not: for it was grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on a rocke. But he that heareth the word, and doth it not, is like a fooliſh man, which hath builded his houſe on the ſand, and the raine fell, and the floods came, and the winde blew, and beat vpon that houſe, and it fell, and the fall of it was great. Temptations therefore and trialls, which are here compared vnto ſtormes and tempeſts, will ſhew what is in all ſorts of men, and whether
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15176:47"/> they haue beene profitable, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable hearers of the word of God; and this is a ſpeciall ende of them, thus to lay open men, both to themſelues, and to the world: when as it ſhall appeare, that in affliction &amp; vnder the croſſe they are the ſame that they were before, or they are not, but farre vnlike.</p>
            <p>After this manner were the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites tried and prooued in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the ſpace of fourtie yeares, in which time ſome of them prooued themſelues murmurers, ſome forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, ſome idolatours, ſome diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ſome faithfull: and all this was by the ſeuerall afflictions and croſſes that did befall them. And thus alſo by the great afflictions that did befall <hi>Iob</hi> in one day, as the loſſe of all his goods and children, it appeared what great vprightnes and ſinceritie, and faithfull obedience was in him: when as he ſaide, Naked came I out of my
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15176:47"/> mothers wombe,<note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> and naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken it: bleſſed be the name of the Lord. And in all this great loſſe he did not ſin, nor charge God fooliſhly.</p>
            <p>For though Satan tooke him to be like other men, and that he ſerued God more for his commodities ſake, becauſe he bleſſed him, then of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and therefore ſaid,<note place="margin">and 1.9.</note> Doth <hi>Iob</hi> feare God for nought? haſt thou not made an hedge about him, and about his houſe, and about all that he hath on euery ſide? thou haſt bleſſed the worke of his hands, and his ſubſtance is increaſed. But ſtretch out now thin hand, and touch all that he hath, to ſee if he will not blaſpheme thee to thy face: and then the Lord ſaid vnto Satan, Loe, all that he hath is in thine hand: and thereupon Satan deſtroied in one day all that he had; and yet he continued in his vprightnes, and was
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15176:48"/> the ſame man that he was before: by this great triall it appeared, that that was true, that the Lord had ſaide of him before: that hee was an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and iuſt man indeede; and one that feared God,<note place="margin">verſ. 10.</note> and eſchewed euill: for all theſe great afflictions could not make him to fall from his former courſe.</p>
            <p>And thus laſtly by triall appeared the great weakenes of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Diſciples, who though as a moſt reſolute man he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.13.</note> Though al men be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thee, yet will I neuer bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; and then Ieſus ſaid vnto him, Verily this night before the cocke crowe, thou ſhalt denie me thrice: &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to him againe, Though I ſhould die with thee, I wil in no caſe denie thee, and ſo ſaid alſo all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples:<note place="margin">47.</note> yet when they ſaw a great multitude with ſwordes and ſtaues from the high Prieſt and Elders of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15176:48"/> the people, and <hi>Iudas</hi> with a kiſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied him into their hands, and ſo they tooke him &amp; led him away; then all the Diſciples fledde. And whereas there ſeemed to be a little more cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in <hi>Peter</hi> then in the reſt,<note place="margin">58.</note> for hee followed Chriſt though a farre off, &amp; ſo came into the high Prieſts hall, and ſate downe with the ſeruants to ſee the ende; yet when he ſaw greater danger like to enſue, &amp; he was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be one of Chriſts Diſciples, at the voice of a maide he grew to be ſo timerous and fearefull, that hee ſware and forſware with curſing and banning, denying Chriſt,<note place="margin">74.</note> euen that euer he ſo much as once knewe the man. Neither himſelfe, nor any other would haue thought that ſo much weakenes ſhould haue broake out from him, before he came to this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; but thereby it was laid open.</p>
            <p>Therefore, if it bee good for vs not to be ignorant of our ſelues, as
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15176:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:15176:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:15176:50"/> indeede hath beene thought to bee a point of greateſt wiſdome, for a man throughly to know himſelfe, that ſo he might not be deceiued with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerweening of himſelfe; if it be good I ſay, for any man to ſee his wants &amp; weakneſſes, that he may be humbled by them, and ſeek to haue them ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; if it be good to know certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we haue receiued ſuch &amp; ſuch graces of the ſpirit of God, &amp; in that meaſure that wee haue, that ſo wee may be thankfull to God for them, &amp; comforted in our ſelues ouer them: Then ſeeing that affliction and the croſſe bringeth forth all this fruit at once, and by triall wee finde what faith, hope, loue, patience, obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp;c. is in vs, and what not; inſomuch, that whatſoeuer we ſeemed to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to our ſelues, and to others, yet now we know certainly that wee are thus and thus, and no otherwiſe: it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be denied but that affliction wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15176:50"/> much good vnto vs, and wee ought vpon experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſay, that we know it to be ſo, euen as the Apoſtle doth here; We knowe that all things worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God.</p>
            <p>Which alſo wee may ſo much the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidently ſay, when we ſhal ſee (omitting to ſpeake of many moe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that the croſſe hath) that laſt and greateſt of all, which is ſpoken of in the verſe following, in theſe words; For thoſe whom he knew before,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.20.</note> he alſo predeſtinate to bee made like to the image of his ſonne, that he might be the firſt borne of many brethren: where he ſheweth this one ende of the croſſe, namely, that thereby wee might bee made like vnto Chriſt in his ſufferings. But before we come to that, we muſt remember that hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we haue ſeene, that there is great vſe of affliction, and that it worketh much good: and therefore wee muſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15176:51"/> conſider that in euery croſſe, beſides the preſent bearing of it, the Lord of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie vnto vs, and worketh it in vs thereby, according to the words of the Text, All things worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God.</p>
            <p>So that as in all other things there is not onely the preſent poſſeſſion, &amp; enioying of them, but there is the vſe and comfort of them; inſomuch that men may haue great ſtore of goods and poſſeſſions, and yet haue no vſe of them, as <hi>Salomon</hi> by his great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome obſerued, and ſet it downe in the booke of the Preacher, ſaying, There is one alone,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.8.</note> and there is not a ſecond, which hath neither ſonne nor daughter, yet is there none ende of his trauaile, neither can his eie bee ſatisfied with riches, neither doth he thinke, for whom doe I trauaile, and defraud my ſoule of pleaſure: Euen ſo many haue great and long croſſes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15176:51"/> vpon them, but make no good vſe of them, neither doe labour after the fruit of them: but God worketh by them their good, in thoſe that bee his.</p>
            <p>Seeing then afflictions are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon both to the good and the bad, and God layeth them vpon them both alike, and they muſt beare them whether they will or no; the one muſt labour for the good which the Lord offereth to them therby, which the other not once ſo much as looke after: of which dutie of theirs, when Gods children are ſomewhat more careleſſe of then they ſhould, then no doubt the Lord in wiſdome and in mercie continueth his rod vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longer; yea, and often increaſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe his purpoſe is to doe them good thereby: and ſo herein dealeth with them as a moſt louing and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der father (as indeede he is) who ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the rod, vntill his childe bee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15176:52"/> thereby humbled, and brought to the confeſſion and amendment of his fault: becauſe his purpoſe is, by his fatherly correction to doe him good.</p>
            <p>Wherein parents often put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene their children and their ſeruants; for often they let their ſeruants alone, and leaue them as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, when they will not profit by words, or a few ſtripes, as not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for them, becauſe they purpoſe not alwaies to be troubled with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but their children, becauſe they ſee that they cannot caſt off naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from them, therfore they leaue them not after once or twice corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but ſtill follow them with the rodde, till they amend: So the Lord, when he ſpareth the wicked in their ſinnes, and reſerueth them for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more heauie iudgement at the laſt, correcting his owne children in the meane ſeaſon againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; he ſheweth that his purpoſe is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15176:52"/> thereby to doe them, aboue all other, much good.</p>
            <p>Therefore let no man in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of his afflictions, though long and grieuous, be too much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, as though the Lord were continually angrie with him, or had a purpoſe to deſtroy and make an ende of him thereby; for he could do that in a moment at once: but let him rather thus thinke with himſelfe, and reaſon but of the word of God; Now I know aſſuredly, that the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me indeede, becauſe hee purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to doe me good by all things, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by affliction, according to his promiſe: and therefore whereas I through the vntowardnes of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, haue not profited ſufficiently by his former chaſtiſements, according to his good meaning towards me, he hath ſent me a new fatherly correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thereby at the laſt to worke my further good: and whereas I tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15176:53"/> the crookedneſſe and vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of my ſinnefull diſpoſition doe not yet profit by them, as hee would haue me; therefore I ſee, that in much mercie and louing kindneſſe he continueth it, that ſo I might get good by it at the laſt.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Lord dealeth with vs like a wiſe and conſcionable Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian; who purpoſing not ſo much to giue phyſicke vnto the ſicke pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and to practiſe on him for his owne gaine, as to cure him by thoſe medicines that he applieth to him, and ſo ſeeketh his health and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: if the firſt medicine will remooue the diſeaſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there he leaueth him, and goes no further; if not, he mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth an other medicine after that, and it may be the third &amp; the fourth, becauſe he hath a care of him, and ſeekes his health. And if at any time he maketh any intermiſſion in the courſe of his phyſicke, and ceaſeth to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15176:53"/> practiſe any further on him, it is not becauſe he meaneth to leaue him, &amp; to giue him ouer, but becauſe of the patients weaknes, that he might ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome further ſtrength, and haue a breathing time to that ende.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo the Lord purpoſing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his gratious promiſe, to doe vs good by affliction, and he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſanctified it by the croſſe of Chriſt to that ende; when by the firſt croſſe we profit not, as we ought, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either he letteth the ſame lie the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vpon vs, that it might do vs good at the laſt; or els taking it away, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an other in ſtead of it to the ſame ende. Which though hee doe not preſently, becauſe we were not then able to indure, yet ſometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, when it ſeemeth beſt to his heauenly wiſdome. Therfore the beſt thing for euery man is, ſoone to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit vnder the croſſe, that God hath laid vpon him, that ſo it might ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15176:54"/> be remooued: and not to labour ſo much for the remoouing of it, as for the fruit of it; leaſt it going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without profit, and not working that in vs, for which God did ſend it, the Lord bring vpon vs ſome greater afterwards, ſeeing it is his purpoſe thereby moſt aſſuredly to doe vs good.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, by this we know, that whereas euery man naturally deſireth that which is beſt for him, and yet moſt men erre in the particulars, they deſiring that which is moſt pleaſant, profitable, and honourable, &amp;c. in this world: which deſires of theirs the Prophet expreſſeth in theſe words;<note place="margin">Pſal 4 6.</note> Many ſay, who will ſhew vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good: By this, I ſay, we know, that that thing indeede is beſt for vs at all times, whatſoeuer it be, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moſt for the glorie of God, for our owne ſaluation, and for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our brethren: which becauſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15176:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lord worketh many times by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, as we haue heard, and often more by them, then by his benefits; we muſt be perſwaded, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are then beſt for euery man which though it be contrarie to mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet it is agreeable to the word of God, &amp; which we ought to beleeue.</p>
            <p>Euen as when a mans bodie is greatly diſtempered with abundance of blood, or ouerladen with ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and groſſe humors, or hath ſome member greatly putrified: then and in theſe reſpects it is beſt for him to haue his blood taken away, and his humors, that his fleſh may be abated, and fall away; yea it is beſt for him in theſe caſes to be launced and cut, to be ſeared; and to haue a part cut off, that the reſt might be ſaued. Which though they be grieuous in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yet at this time they are moſt profitable, and to be deſired. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when any affliction or calamitie
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15176:55"/> doth befall vs, let vs not be diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith, as with that that is hurtfull for vs, neither be too impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and wearie, as of a thing that we would faine be ridde of; but ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our iudgements and wills to the iudgement and will of God reuealed in his word, let vs quietly indure, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that euen now the Lord giueth vs that, not which we fondly deſire, as the beſt; but which he knoweth to be, and is indeede at this time the beſt.</p>
            <p>Seeing then it is ſo, (for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clearing of this truth) what I pray you is the cauſe, why not onely the wicked and vngodly, who are not able to iudge of this matter, by all the wit and reaſon that they haue; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the very godly, who beeing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened by the ſpirit of God, ought to know this doctrine to be true, and to beleeue it, that they, I ſay, doe ſo grieuouſly complaine of their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15176:55"/> as thoſe which are the worſt for them that can be? and as thoſe that ſhould not onely doe them no good, but much hurt: when as wee haue ſeene alreadie how many waies they worke their good, and therefore are the beſt for them indeede.</p>
            <p>Why did <hi>Iob,</hi> ſeeing his afflictions were ſent vnto him by God for his triall, and for his good, why did he ſo complaine of them?<note place="margin">Iob 6.2.</note> Oh that my griefe were well waied, and my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries were laid together in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance? for it would now be heauier then the ſand of the ſea: therefore my words are ſwallowed vp. For the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the Almightie are in me, the venime thereof doth drinke vp my ſpirit, and the terrours of God fight againſt me, &amp;c. Why doth <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> alſo make ſo grieuous complaints in reſpect of the affliction that did befall him, when he beginneth the Pſalme thus lamentably; O Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15176:56"/> me not in thine anger, neither chaſtiſe me in thy wrath: for thine arrows haue light vpon me, and thine hand lieth vpon me: there is nothing ſound in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger, neither is there reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſin. My wounds are putrified and corrupt; I am bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and crooked very ſore; I go mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the day: for my reines are full of burning, and there is nothing ſound in my fleſh: my heart panteth, and my ſtrength faileth, and the light of mine eyes, euen they are not mine owne, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If theſe afflictions of theirs did worke their good, why did they thus complaine of them? Truely it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but that men for the moſt part doe more complaine of their afflictions, then they ought to doe, and are more full of murmuring and impatiencie vnder the hand of God, then they ſhould be: and they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15176:56"/> doe not ſo comfortably beare their croſſes as they ſhould and might yet all this hindereth not, but that the Lord by them ſeeketh their good, &amp; they ſhould labour to profit, &amp; to be bettered by their afflictions, and bee perſwaded that they ſhall worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the beſt vnto them, thogh they be full of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints, whiles they are in the middeſt of them. For who euer complained more of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, then theſe two men, <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> and yet who had more profit, or gote more good by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then they? both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being thus tried, &amp; in the triall found to bee moſt faithfull and patient, and conſtant vnto the ende.</p>
            <p>And concerning this proneneſſe in vs to complaine, we muſt conſider that ſuch is our nature, that we muſt needes haue the feeling of our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, vnleſſe our hearts were harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, like yron or ſteele, and ſo wee were ſenſleſſe like ſtocks and ſtones,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15176:57"/> and not as men. And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is otherwiſe, namly, our hearts naturally are ſoft and tender, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be broken with affliction, and ſome more, and ſome leſſe; it cannot poſſibly be, but that euery thing that befalleth vs, ſhould worke vpon vs, and that we ſhould bee mooued ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature and qualitie of it; either to ioy or ſorrow, loue or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, anger or feare, and ſuch like: &amp; therefore tribulation muſt needes trouble vs, and affliction muſt needs afflict vs, and the croſſe cannot but crucifie vs; &amp; yet we may and ought for all that bee perſwaded, that it is for our good, and looke for it from thence, and pray to God in faith that we may finde it.</p>
            <p>Euen as the ſicke patient, &amp; pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full languiſhing creature vnder the Phyſitians hand, cannot as he is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, indued with ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but feele to his great griefe the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15176:57"/> launcing with ſharpe kniues, and the ſearing of his fleſh with redde hotte yrons, &amp; ſo complaine of them with much heauineſſe, and many teares; yea crie out and roare for the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his paine, though he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it be beſt for him then thus to be handled: and therefore though he be ſometimes bound in the dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing both hand and foote, or violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly held by men; yet after a ſort hee doth moſt willingly ſuffer it. And this is one cauſe of complaining in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though they are perſwaded that it is for their good, euen the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie and tendernes of our nature, whereby all croſſes worke on vs as they doe.</p>
            <p>But there is an other cauſe more principall then this, which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or want of faith: for many are too full of complaints in their affliction, becauſe they are not perſwaded at all, or not at that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15176:58"/> time, when they are in temptation, that aduerſitie, or the croſſe is for their good; or at leaſt not that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular croſſe, and in that manner, that it is vpon them: which if they could come vnto, whatſoeuer ſhould be laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, they would not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complaine of it, for the hope of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good would mitigate and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage all. Therefore all ſuch are to meditate vpon that which hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die beene ſpoken concerning this matter; namely, how many waies by affliction the Lord doth vs good.</p>
            <p>In the latter part of the verſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, To them that loue God; that is, all things worke together for the beſt vnto them that loue God: as he thereby reſtraineth this general pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, becauſe it is not made to all; ſo he ſheweth to whome it appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; namely, to thoſe that beleeue in Chriſt, and are ſanctified by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whereof this is one ſpeciall fruit;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15176:58"/> The loue of God. For he intreateth here of the certentie of the ſaluation of thoſe that belong vnto Chriſt, as appeareth by the firſt words of the chapter;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> Now then there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. Where he alſo diſcerneth the true beleeuer from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by this fruit of faith, namely, ſanctification; &amp; here he doth name one principall of it, which is loue: Loue to God, from whence ariſeth loue vnto men for his ſake, and from them both, all duties to God and man.</p>
            <p>And thus the Apoſtle alſo in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ioyneth faith and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as thoſe that are inſeparable, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Gal. 5 6.</note> that in Ieſus Chriſt neither circumciſion nor vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion auaileth any thing: but faith, which worketh by loue: where his meaning is, that no outward thing, or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15176:59"/> ſeruice of God, though commanded by him, as circumciſion was, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth vs to God, or maketh vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, but onely Chriſt, and his obedience: which we take hold of, and ſo make ours by faith: which faith is then effectual and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when it breedeth in vs a loue, which loue appeareth by the fruits and effects of the ſame. So then the Apoſtle here vnder one fruit, which is loue, comprehendeth all godlines, and ſanctification.</p>
            <p>But hee taketh this thing rather then any other, (The loue of God) as that, that is moſt fit for his purpoſe: for ſpeaking of affliction he ſaith, that by this we ſhall trie our faith, if our loue to God continue euen then: ſo that wee ceaſe not to loue God, though he afflict vs. For whereas the very wicked will pretend to loue God in proſperitie, and as long as all things goe well with them, they will
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15176:59"/> profeſſe that they loue God, as much as any, yea; and that they were worſe then the bruit beaſts, if that they did not loue him, and that with all their heart, who beſtoweth all things vpon them ſo liberally, and many ſuch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious words they will vtter: but in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, and when God layeth affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vpon them, their loue is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: yea, they fall into open hatred and defiance with God, yea euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plaine curſing and banning; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the example of <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, who ſaide vnto her husband;<note place="margin">Iob 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Doeſt thou continue ſtill in thine vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, blaſpheme God, and die. But he that loueth God truly, loueth him not for his backe and belly, as we ſay, but becauſe he is goodnes it ſelfe, and therefore principally to be beloued for himſelfe: and ſo their loue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth, though all outward bleſſings be taken away.</p>
            <p>And herein the wicked too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15176:60"/> bewray vile mindes, and ſeruile natures; that like as ſeruants loue not their maſters, nor maidens their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, if they once beginne to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them for their faults; &amp; ſo grow wearie of them, and are readie to run away from them: as the maid ſeruant <hi>Hagar</hi> the Egyptian did from her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe <hi>Sarai.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 16.6.</note> But the godly doe this way as apparantly ſhew their liberall nature, and ingenuous diſpoſition; in that as no correction or ſtripes of the father or mother, can make the child to change his loue to them, &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to alienate his minde from them, much leſſe can they driue him cleane away from them, but he will abide in their houſe, and in all his neede reſort to them for ſuccour: ſo will they ſtill in affliction loue God, and depend vpon him for all things needfull.</p>
            <p>And this corruption to be in the nature of all men generally, euen by affliction to fall away from the loue
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15176:60"/> and ſeruice of God, Satan knew well enough, and therefore thought to haue found it in <hi>Iob,</hi> though he did not, when he ſaide vnto the Lord, Doth <hi>Iob</hi> loue, or feare,<note place="margin">Iob 1.9.</note> or ſerue God for nought? as if he had ſaid, he doth not ſerue thee for thine owne ſake, or for any loue that hee beareth vnto thee, but for the commoditie that he receiueth by thee: for he addeth, Haſt not thou made an hedge about him, and about his houſe, and about all that he hath on euery ſide: thou haſt bleſſed the worke of his hands, &amp; his ſubſtance is increaſed in the land: but ſtretch out thine hand, and touch all that he hath, to ſee if he will not bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme thee to thy face. In which words he noteth that vice, that men commonly are ſubiect vnto, that is, to hide their rebellion in proſperitie, and in aduerſitie to bewray it.</p>
            <p>Therefore if we be free from this vice, and ſo ceaſe not in affliction to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15176:61"/> loue God, and in loue to ſerue him, we ſhall be ſure, that he will fulfil this promiſe of his vnto vs, of turning all things to our good: and cauſing all our croſſes to make together for the beſt vnto vs, ſo long as we loue God: and this vnfained loue that we finde we beare in our hearts vnto God, is a ſure teſtimonie vnto vs of it, and we ought thereby to be perſwaded of the vndoubted truth of it, &amp; ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues for the time preſent, that God will doe vs good by this correction of his, euen becauſe wee loue him.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, ſeeing that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles purpoſe here is, to intreat of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in affliction, and to prepare vs for it; this no doubt is moſt fit for the fame, namely, the conſideration of that loue, which we ought to beare vnto God, whereby we might be mooued to take all things in good part, that he ſends vnto vs, becauſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15176:61"/> we loue him, and in loue are deſirous to pleaſe him. For we ſee daily in all worldly matters, what great things all ſorts of men will beare at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of them, whome they loue: as how many grieuous things doth the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put vp at the hands of her fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward child, whome ſhee tenderly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth? And the husband paſſeth ouer with ſilence many things that are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue proceeding from his wife, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee is deare vnto him, and his loue towards her cauſeth him not to regard them; yea for her ſake he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with many things at the hands of others.</p>
            <p>As it is ſaid of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29.20.</note> that he ſerued <hi>Laban</hi> a very hard maſter ſeuen years for <hi>Rahel,</hi> during which time he tooke great paines day and night:<note place="margin">&amp; 31.40.</note> for in the day he was conſumed with heat, and with froſt in the night, and his wages was changed ten times: yet they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him but a fewe daies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15176:62"/> he loued her: thus loue vnto men cauſeth vs to indure hard things for their ſakes whome we loue: and the more we loue them, the more willingly to gratifie them doe wee chearefully vndergoe any hard ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for them. How much more then ought we patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to beare all things at the hand of God, whom we know, that he ſo loued vs, that he ſpared not his owne ſonne,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> but gaue him for vs all to death: and therefore we ought to loue him aboue all other things, yea aboue our ſelues againe.</p>
            <p>And no doubt wee would thus beare all croſſes laid vpon vs by God for our good, a great deale more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently then we doe, if there were in vs that loue vnto his maieſtie, that there ought.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13 5.</note> For loue ſeeketh not her owne things: that is, it is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of loue, not ſo much to ſeeke to ſatisfie their owne minde, as to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the partie whome they loue, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:15176:62"/> in things oſten contrary to their own liking: therefore let vs labour for that pure &amp; ſincere loue vnto God, which may abide in the greateſt affliction, ſo ſhall we not onely patiently beare them, but be aſſured, that they ſhall be turned vnto our good: according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle here; All things worke together for the beſt vnto them, that loue God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When he addeth theſe wordes in the ende of the ſame verſe, (which are called of his purpoſe) as he doth in them further ſhew to whome this promiſe doth appertaine, namely, that all afflictions ſhall worke for their beſt: euen vnto ſuch as are effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called vnto the knowledge of their ſaluation in Chriſt, according to the good purpoſe and decree of God towards them: So he ſheweth the cauſe, why all afflictions are made profitable vnto them eſpecially, and turned vnto their good in the ende:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15176:63"/> which is not any worthines of theirs, that they deſerue it at Gods hands, or any right behauing themſelues vnder the croſſe, as though they were able to worke it out themſelues; for of themſelues they are as weake, and fraile, and impatient vnder it, as any other: but the free loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in Chriſt, whereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of the world, he purpoſed to do them good, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in time effectually called them. Which purpoſe of his nothing can alter, but he maketh all things to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it, yea ſometimes contrarie to their nature, as afflictions.</p>
            <p>So that from the firſt vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe of their ſaluation, and of all good intented towardes them, he ſheweth the certentie of this, that all afflictions ſhall worke together for the beſt to thoſe that loue God: for who can hinder or fruſtrate the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate purpoſe of God in any
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15176:63"/> thing? None in the world, no not the deuill himſelfe: and therefore afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can not hinder the good that he meaneth to his children, becauſe he hath purpoſed to doe them good. Which purpoſe of his for their good hath alway appeared by their fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and effectuall calling. For when he had purpoſed to ſaue them by his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, he called them by the miniſterie of the Goſpel in his good time ſome ſooner ſome later vnto the knowledge of it; and from the ſame purpoſe of his it came to paſſe, that the word was made effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall vnto them by the inward ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his holy Spirit, working in them faith and repentance: and ſo became vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The power of God vnto their ſaluation,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> as the Apoſtle calleth it: that is, the mightie and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall inſtrument of God to worke their ſaluation, when it was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable vnto others, that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15176:64"/> heard it, as well as they.</p>
            <p>So then the Lord continuing the ſame purpoſe of his towards them, it ſhall vndoubtedly come to paſſe, that though al other men ſhould not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by their afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but waxe worſe and worſe, as commonly the wicked doe, as we ſee in the example of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh king of Egypt, who after many grieuous plagues brought vpon him,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.35.</note> and vpon the whole land, one after an other, his heart was ſtill more and more hardned, neither would he let the children of Iſrael goe: yet the Lord would turne all this to their good, becauſe he had purpoſed it. And for the certentie and full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this, he leadeth them to the conſideration of the purpoſe of God appearing in their calling, which beeing very ſtrange, and many things to the outward appearance againſt it, yet the Lord brake through them all, and none of them could hinder it,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15176:64"/> or ſtay it, becauſe God had purpoſed it.</p>
            <p>And truly it is worthie our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to remember how many things haue beene in the way to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the calling of men vnto ſaluation, yet none of them could doe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had purpoſed. As who would euer haue thought,<note place="margin">Act. 9.1.</note> that <hi>Paul</hi> ſometimes called <hi>Saul,</hi> breathing out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples of the Lord, and hauing now in this great furie and rage of his obtained letters of the high Prieſt to Damaſcus, that if he found any that were of that way or profeſſion, (either men or women) he might bring them bound vnto Ieruſalem: ſhould at this time be ſo ſuddenly conuerted, that he ſhould not onely become a Chriſtian, but an Apoſtle: ſo that it ſhould be truly ſaid of him, he which was a great perſecutor in time paſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.22.</note> now is a zealous preacher
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15176:65"/> of the faith, which before he deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but he ſhewes the cauſe of it there himſelfe,<note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> when he ſaith, that God had ſeparated him thereunto from his mothers wombe, and ſo called him vnto it of his grace: that is, in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting counſell he firſt appointed him to be an Apoſtle, and ſecondari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euen from his birth he did ſeparate him to this office; and thirdly, in time of his meere grace and fauour he called him vnto it, according to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of ſome other, as of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> king of Iudah,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 33 2.</note> who doing euill in the ſight of the Lord like the abominations of the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſetting vp altars for Baalim, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping all the hoaſt of heauen, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing alſo his ſonnes to paſſe through the fire in the valley of Ben-hinnom: and giuing himſelf to witchcraft and to charming, and vſing them that had familiar ſpirits; there was no likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15176:65"/> that he ſhould be conuerted vnto God, there were ſo many things againſt it: but the Lord, that had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſhew him mercie, did bring him vnto it againſt all theſe: for he cauſed the King of Aſhur to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, who tooke him priſoner,<note place="margin">verſ 11.</note> and put him in fetters, and bound him in chaines, and caried him to Babel; and when he was in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he praied to the Lord his God, &amp; humbled himſelfe greatly before the God of his fathers; and praied vnto him, and God was intreated of him, and heard his praier: and then he knew that the Lord was God.</p>
            <p>But to let theſe paſſe; let euery man conſider the manner of his own calling, &amp; ſee how many things were within him, and without him, that might haue hindred him from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to that meaſure of grace, that he hath now receiued, that ſo he may acknowledge vpon his owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15176:66"/> that nothing is able to hinder the good purpoſe of God towardes thoſe that loue him. And then he ſhal finde, that the great ignorance, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, or Atheiſme, in which all his kinred were left might haue ſtaied this good worke, but that God did draw him out of them, as he did A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> commanding him to forſake his countrey, and his kinred, and his fathers houſe: or that the manifold great corruptions that were rooted in vs, and confirmed by cuſtome, like vnto the ſeauen deuills that were in Marie Magdalen, might haue kept vs from the hope of it: or the looſe and diſſolute life that we lead, miſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding our time, and the gifts of God, our wit and ſtrength in riotouſnes and wantonnes, as the prodigall childe did; might haue kept Gods good hand from vs: or that we did deſpiſe and tread vnder our feet the pretious pearle of Gods word, when it was
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15176:66"/> offered vnto vs, like vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane beaſts, or ſwine that Chriſt ſpeaketh of in the Goſpel: or that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things els might in the iudgement of all men haue beene as a barre to keepe vs from an effectuall calling; but that the Lord in much mercy had purpoſed it, and ſo according to the ſame purpoſe of his, he bore all things downe before him, and came tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough them vnto vs for our good.</p>
            <p>And ſo we ſhall be the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the Lord of the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable goodneſſe of his hauing purpoſed euen by the croſſe, and all manner of affliction to doe vs good, how many things ſo euer may ſeeme to our ſelues, or to others to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, that he will verifie this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto vs, and we ſhall find it to be true, as well as others, that all things ſhall worke for the beſt to thoſe that loue God, euen thoſe that are called of his purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:15176:67"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note>In the next verſe when he addeth; For thoſe whome he knew before, he alſo predeſtinate, to be like to the image of his ſonne, that he might be the firſt borne of many brethren: he declareth an other moſt excellent ende, wherefore the Lord laieth the croſſe moſt of all vpon his children: namely, that thereby they might be like vnto Chriſt their eldeſt brother, as the Lord hath ordained, that all that are his ſhould be, ſome more, &amp; ſome leſſe. And ſo by this meanes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially it worketh our good, when it maketh vs the members conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and like vnto Chriſt our head. In which words he not onely ſaith, that all afflictions doe befall vs by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeciall prouidence and hand of God, and not by fortune or chance: but alſo he ſheweth, to what ende he ſendeth them;<note place="margin">Luk. 24.26</note> namely, that as Chriſt himſelf firſt ſuffered, and then entred into glorie: ſo all others going the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15176:67"/> ſame way, that he did, they might be like vnto him; as the Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that they ſhould be. And therefore we neede not to feare, that the croſſe ſhould hinder vs from our ſaluation, no more then it did Chriſt from glory: but rather that we ought in the midſt of it to haue ſuch hope, that we ſhall be like vnto Chriſt in glorie, becauſe we are like vnto him in the croſſe: according as it is ſaid in an other place, If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo raigne with him.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the former of theſe two points, namely, that no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction commeth by caſualtie, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falleth vs by happe hazard, as we ſay, neither that any thing is done by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune or chance, but by the very ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all appointment of God: he not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly willingly ſuffering it, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, and vs in it with his own eies, but laying it vpon vs himſelfe, euen with his owne hands, and firſt of all
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15176:68"/> ordaining it: this, I ſay, not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it moſt notable comfort, and ſingular conſolation, conſidered alone and apart by it ſelfe: but alſo is that, vnto which the whole Scripture of the old &amp; new Teſtament beareth very plentiful witnes. For ſeeing that we beleeue, according to the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our faith, that God made all things of nothing, therefore alſo we are aſſured, that whatſoeuer are the means knowne or vnknowne, of any thing that befalleth vs, that the Lord himſelfe is the doer of the ſame: for that which they did, they did by his ſpeciall power, ſeeing that of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they were firſt nothing, and therfore without him could not doe any thing.</p>
            <p>And thus the Pſalmiſt profeſſeth his faith, in the name of the reſt of the ſeruants of God, acknowledging that the Lord himſelfe hath brought all their troubles vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which they
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15176:68"/> ſuffered by the violence and crueltie of their aduerſaries; and that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone did in the ende deliuer them out of their hands: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpeaketh thus, Praiſe our God, ye people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.8.</note> and make the voice of his praiſe to be heard; which holdeth our ſoules in life, and ſuffereth not our feete to ſlippe. For thou, O God, haſt prooued vs, thou haſt tried vs as ſiluer is tried; thou haſt brought vs into the ſnares, and laid a ſtrait chaine vpon our loines: thou haſt cauſed men to ride ouer our heads: we went into fire and into water, but thou broughteſt vs out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a wealthie place: where they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that though men did ſo oppreſſe them, as though they ſhould ride o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, yet that the Lord cauſed them ſo to doe, and he brought them into the ſnare, and by the crueltie of tyrants laid a ſtrait chaine vpon their loynes, which pinched them: and ſo he did not onely behold their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15176:69"/> but by them did of purpoſe trie them, as men doe ſiluer.</p>
            <p>Whereunto agreeth that moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſaying of <hi>Iob,</hi> containing the like profeſſion of his faith in this very point; that God bringeth all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon men, though he vſeth men, or any other meanes, or the deuill himſelfe, as inſtruments and meanes to work vnder him in the ſame thing. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satan had deſired the Lord to ſtretch out his hand,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.11.</note> and touch <hi>Iob</hi> in his poſſeſſions, to ſee what would become of him then: and thereupon the Lord ſaide vnto him, Loe all that he hath is in thine hand. then he ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the Shabeans, who came vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently and caried away all his oxen, as they were plowing, and his aſſes as they were ſeeding: and he cauſed fire to come downe and burne vp his ſheepe and his ſeruants that kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and he mooued the Chaldeans to ſet vpon his camels; and to carie them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15176:69"/> and to ſlay his ſeruants: and he raiſed vp a tempeſt of winde, which blewe downe the houſe where his ſonnes and his daughters were, and ſlew them all. And when the tidings of all theſe were brought vnto him on the ſudden, then he fell downe vpon the ground,<note place="margin">verſ. 20.</note> and worſhipped God, ſaying, Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken it: bleſſed be the name of the Lord. Thus though he ſaw the meanes of his vndoing, yet he looked vp to God, and confeſſed him to be the principall doer in this buſines: not aſcribing his loſſes vnto the Chaldeans or Sabeans, but vnto God working by them: and therfore he ſaid, The Lord hath taken away.</p>
            <p>Thus we ought ſo beleeue and confeſſe, that whatſoeuer doth befall vs either by wicked or vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or by Satan himſelfe, and all his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15176:70"/> helliſh power, that the Lord is the doer of the ſame: for the very deuills themſelues were conſtrained to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge vnto Chriſt, when he was vpon the earth, that they could doe nothing without his permiſſion, or rather without his warrant and ſpeciall commaundement: and that not onely vnto men, but euen to the worſt and meaneſt of his creatures. For when he was in the countrey of the Gergaſeus, there met him two men poſſeſſed with many deuills;<note place="margin">Matth. 8.28.</note> and the deuills ſpeaking in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beſought him, ſaying, If thou caſt vs out, ſuffer vs to goe into the heard of ſwine; which was feeding a farre off vpon an hill: ſo they all confeſſe, that they were not able to enter into thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bruit beaſts to hurt them, vntill ſuch time as Chriſt gaue them leaue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 5.12.</note>But <hi>S. Marke</hi> ſpeaketh of it more ſignificantly, namely, that they ſaid vnto him, Send vs into the ſwine: and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15176:70"/> then as <hi>S. Matthew</hi> ſaith, he did not onely ſuffer them, and giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue ſo to doe, but bade them goe, and ſo ſent them to them: whereupon they entred into them, and caried them headlong from the hill into the ſea, and ſo choaked them there. So that they confeſſe, that they could doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but by the power of Chriſt, ſending them, ruling them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining them at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo it is written of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.1.</note> that he was lead aſide of the Spirit of God into the wildernes, to be tempted of the deuill; to ſhew vs, that whatſoeuer did befall him there, the Lord God ſent him thither, and to that end: and that God was not onely contented to ſuffer him to be diuers waies tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by the ſpace of fourtie daies, and fourtie nights continually; but that he went thither by the immediate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Spirit of God for the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15176:71"/> ſame ende and purpoſe: who could otherwiſe haue preſerued him, that the Deuill ſhould haue had nothing to doe with him. And according to this dealing of God with him, Chriſt hath taught vs all thus to pray, Lord lead vs not into temptation:<note place="margin">Luk. 11.4.</note> which kind of wordes, as they be agreeable vnto the words of the Euangeliſts, yea of our Sauiour Chriſt, So they are more full of faith and comfort, then if we ſhould ſay, as many had wont to doe, Suffer vs not to be lead into temptation: becauſe therein we confeſſe, not onely that the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth vs in our troubles, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs to be lead into them, and ſo is in thoſe things a looker on; but that he, that is our father, and therefore loueth vs; who made vs, and therfore knoweth our ſtrength, laieth them vpon our backes himſelfe, and doth not as it were ſtand by till an other doth it: and therefore we neede ſo
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15176:71"/> much the leſſe to feare, leſt we ſhould be ouerladen with them: for as it is ſaid in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> as a father hath compaſſion on his children, ſo hath the Lord compaſſion on them that feare him: for he knoweth whereof we be made, he remembreth that we are but duſt.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this ſhould not onely make vs patient in all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and willingly to beare them, becauſe they come from God, that loueth vs: but alſo to looke for ſome good from them in the ende, becauſe that he, who hath promiſed to worke our good thereby, doth lay them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs himſelfe. And vnleſſe we be thus perſwaded of them, we ſhall be readie to fret, and ſtorme, and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to beare them; much more ſhall we thinke them to be for our hurt, rather then for our good. If <hi>Iob</hi> when he loſt all, if he had looked vnto the violence and robberie of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans<note place="margin">Iob 1.15.</note>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:15176:72"/> and Sabeans; who ſpoiled him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to the malice of the Deuill, who ſet them a worke, and had gone no further, he muſt needes haue had a number of reuenging thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and he could no waies haue put it vp at their hands; but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he conſidered of the prouidence of God working by them in wiſdome and mercie, beyond that that fleſh &amp; and blood could conceiue: and was reſolued of this, that the Lord had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all away: that made him patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beare all, and to giue thanks vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; and not to vtter one fooliſh word,<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> or to offend with his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen 37.24.</note>And this made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> patiently to put vp thoſe iniuries and wrongs that were offered vnto him by his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren; when as firſt of all they caſt him into an emptie pit, that there he might periſh: and afterwards they drew him out of it, and ſolde him to the Iſhmaelites, who brought him
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15176:72"/> into Egypt. Where afterwardes he beeing aduanced vnto great honour, when in the time of famine his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren came thither to buie corne, and he at their ſecond comming made himſelfe knowne vnto them; ſaying, Come neere, I pray you to me:<note place="margin">&amp; 45.4.</note> I am Ioſeph your brother, whome ye ſold into Egypt: but he ſtaieth not there: for then he might in ſome great heat of affection haue expoſtulated the matter with them, and haue don the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome harme, ſeeing he had power in his hands: but he addeth further for their comfort, and to ſhew what ſtaied him: Be not ſad,<note place="margin">v. 5.</note> neither grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with your ſelues, that ye ſold me hither: for God did ſend me before you for your preſeruation: for now two yeares of famine haue been tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the land, and fiue yeares are behind, wherein ſhall be neither ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, nor harueſt: wherfore God ſent me before you, to preſerue your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15176:73"/> in this land, and to ſaue you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue by a great deliuerance. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſent me not hither, but God, who hath made me a father vnto Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh, and lord of all his houſe, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler throughout all the land of Egypt. Where we ſee, how he turneth his eyes from his brethren, and looketh vnto God, ſaying it was not they that ſold him, but God that ſent him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that for the good of them all: and this made him ſo patiently to beare it.</p>
            <p>And thus the Lord, though he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth ſuch ſinnes as theſe in men, yet he often vſeth them to his glorie: which when men can wiſely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of, and diſcerne the one from the other, it will make them quietly to beare great things at the hands of men, becauſe they ſtay not in them, but caſt vp their eyes vnto God: whereas if they ſhould onely looke vnto men, and goe no further, they
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15176:73"/> know that they in their doings mean them no good, but hurt: and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they haue deſerued no ſuch meaſure at their hands, they would be like the dogge that bites the ſtaffe wherwith he is beaten, and conſiders not of him that ſtriketh him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all afflictions, let vs beleeue that we haue to deale with God, ſo ſhall we be patient, and comfortable vnder the ſame. And this is that, no doubt, that ſtaied the old man <hi>Heli</hi> the Prieſt, when he heard that meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from the Lord by <hi>Samuel,</hi> which otherwiſe would haue beene a great deale more vncomfortable vnto him, as appeareth by his words, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that he gaue vnto him. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he told him, that God would iudge his houſe for euer,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> for the iniquitie which he knew, becauſe his ſonnes ranne into a ſlaunder, and he ſtaied them not; then he anſwered,<note place="margin">18.</note> It is the Lord: let him doe what ſeemeth him
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15176:74"/> good. This faith, that he knew, that all things ſhould fall out not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of man, but of God, was that, that gaue him hope of a good iſſue of all thoſe troubles in the ende: and ſo it muſt doe to vs.</p>
            <p>For this is all one, as if the ſicke patient ſhould haue a Phiſitian to deale with him, who were his father, his brother, or his friend: who ſhould not onely preſcribe the quantitie of all the ingredients for his medicine, knowing well the qualities and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them; but ſhould alſo make the confection himſelfe, bring it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and miniſter it with his owne hands: of whoſe fidelitie and care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and deſire of his health, becauſe he doubteth not one whit; that would make him moſt willing to receiue it, though very bitter and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant: and though at the firſt he found it in the working ſomewhat churliſh, yet he would hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15176:74"/> ſome good by it in the ende; knowing who made it, and brought it vnto him.</p>
            <p>And after this manner, and vnder this very compariſon, our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh of his owne afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did moſt willingly indure the croſſe, which others would haue put off from him, becauſe it was that, that his father did lay vpon him. For when <hi>Iudas</hi> and the reſt came with weapons to take him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> hauing a ſword drew it out, &amp; laid about him, hoping to haue reſcued him out of their hands: and ſtriking at the head of one of the ſeruants of the high Prieſt, cut off his right eare.<note place="margin">11.</note> Then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaide vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> Put vp thy ſword into the ſheath: ſhall I not drinke of the cuppe, which my father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me? Wherein he ſheweth not onely what made him ſo patient, and what cauſed him to ſtay Peter, euen the will of his Father: but thereby he
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15176:75"/> doth alſo teach vs, that whenſoeuer any croſſe doth befal vs, it is that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and cuppe, which God our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in great wiſdome and mercie hath mingled for vs: and therefore we ſhould not feare any hurt by drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it, but rather take it willingly, and hope that it ſhall work our good, according to his meaning towards vs, and as he hath promiſed in his word.</p>
            <p>If when the child hath offended his father, he ſhould ſay to one of his ſeruants in his anger; Take him out of my ſight, and puniſh him ſo and ſo: this would be more grieuous and fearefull a great deale vnto an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous child, then if the father ſhould take correction of him himſelfe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was better perſwaded of the goodnes of his father towards him, then of the ſeruants, and ſo might looke for more mercie from the one, then from the other, Euen ſo it may
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15176:75"/> miniſter vnto vs no ſmall comfort in all our afflictions, that we beleeue, that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are vnder our fathers hand, and he himſelfe dealeth with vs, and that he hath not in his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure deliuered vs to any other to be tormented by them.</p>
            <p>Againe, if one that were blinde, offending his father, ſhould be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly taken away, and caried to ſome puniſhment, he knew not whether, nor by whome, he might iuſtly feare what would be the ende and meaſure of it: but if he knew it were his father, part of his feare would be diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he would be the leſſe vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to goe with him, and more qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly ſubmit himſelfe vnto his corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So we if at any time through our ignorance and blindnes doe not rightly conceiue of our croſſes, and of the author of them; but as vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine we aſcribe them to this, or to that, or to we know not what, we are
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15176:76"/> ſo much the more timerous &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: but if the eyes of our minde by faith in Gods word be ſo opened, that we ſee clearely God to be the author of them, and that we are in the hands of none but of our father; our minds are ſo much the more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and we ſhall finde a wonderful alteration in our ſelues, ouer that was in vs before, in reſpect of the patient bearing of our preſent eſtate, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be.</p>
            <p>Or (to ſhew it in an other compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon) if one ſhould be ſo hardly dealt withall, as is the manner in the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Inquiſition; in which men are examined for their faith in Chriſt, and religion to God, that the poore ſoule might be put into the greater feare, and ſo the ſooner abjure his faith; if he ſhould haue a tormentor ſent vnto him very ougly diſguiſed, more like a deuill then a man, who ſhould carie him into ſome dark dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15176:76"/> he knew not whether, and there lay him vpon the racke: this would no doubt increaſe the griefe of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction ſo much the more, becauſe he knew not who did deal with him, and ſo could looke for no mercie at his hands. But now, if when he were in the midſt of his torture he ſhould heare the voice of his father ſpeaking vnto him, though thus diſguiſed, that might ſomewhat vphold him, and ridde him of a number of thoughts that he was troubled with before.</p>
            <p>So all afflictions muſt needes be ſo much the more vncomfortable vnto vs, as long as we looke not vp vnto him, that ſendeth it; and are ſo blind, that we conſider not, who ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs. Yet when we heare out of the word the voice of our father ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto vs, and telling vs that it is he that dealeth with vs, how ſtraunge and deformed ſo euer the tormentor may ſeeme to be, that is, how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15176:77"/> and vnlooked for ſo euer the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction be, and contrarie to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; let vs not be too much diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, becauſe that then when he ſtriketh vs, he ſtill loueth vs, and the bowels of his compaſſion doe yearne vpon vs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. king. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.26.</note> more then in a mother to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her childe, when ſhee ſeeth what harme is like to come vnto it: and he then ſeeketh thereby to doe vs good.</p>
            <p>And this is that, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie ſpeaketh of in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Lord, ſhewing how he ſtandeth affected towards them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth moſt of all afflict the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Where firſt of all he bringeth in the Church of the Iewes ſorowing for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their affliction, which God had laid vpon them for their ſinnes: and in the ſame committing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wholly to God, and praying to him for his ſaluation; when he ſaith, I haue heard Ephraim lamenting<note place="margin">Ier. 31.18.</note>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:15176:77"/> thus thou haſt corrected me, and I was chaſtiſed as an vntamed calfe; conuert thou me, and I ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted: for thou art the Lord my God; ſurely after I was conuerted, I repented: and after that I was inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, I ſmote vpon my thigh: I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, yea confounded, becauſe I did beare the reproach of my youth. Then the Lord maketh this anſwer, that he had not caſt them off, though he had ſo afflicted them, but did ſtill loue them, and when he did moſt of all afflict them, then he was mooued with pitie and compaſſion towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying, Is Ephraim my deare ſon,<note place="margin">v. 20.</note> or pleaſant child? I ſurely: for ſince I ſpake vnto him, I ſtill remembred him: therefore my bowels are troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for him, I will ſurely haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vpon him, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, that all afflictions are ordained, and ſent of God, &amp; that for our good, &amp; that he beareth the ſame
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15176:78"/> fatherly affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards vs in them, that he did before. And therefore that the ſaluation of the Church, and of euery member of the ſame is by Gods decree ioyned with bearing the croſſe: in ſo much that we are not to looke to be free from it, vnleſſe we will peruert this order eſtabliſhed by God himſelfe. Neither neede we to feare it, when as the Lord, who hath determined to ſaue vs, hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this way and meanes alſo to ſaue vs by, and to worke our good: and ſo his decree and purpoſe of ſauing vs can not be ſeuered from his decree of exerciſing vs vnder the croſſe.</p>
            <p>And that none of vs all might looke to be freed from the croſſe, or feare, that it ſhould hinder vs in our ſaluation, or in any gift that might further vs thereunto: the Apoſtle tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, wherfore the Lord hath thus decreed of the whole Church, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them vnder the croſſe; namely,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15176:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeeing that his owne dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne,<note place="margin">Math. 3.17.</note> in whome he is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, (as it was teſtified from heauen) ſeeing that he came no other way but by the croſſe vnto his great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to be ſet at the right hand of God: he beeing the eldeſt brother in the houſe of God, all other by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and obedience to the croſſe, might yeild vnto him ſoueraigntie, and acknowledge him to be chiefe, when they will not refuſe to goe that way to their inheritance, which Chriſt went before, the eldeſt and onely naturall ſonne of God, though it ſeeme neuer ſo grieuous, euen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough many afflictions.</p>
            <p>For euen as a noble man wil haue all his ſeruants to weare one liuerie, and all of them to haue the ſame cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, that they may be knowne whoſe they are: So the Lord would haue all his ſeruants and children, to be knowne from the reſt of the world
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15176:79"/> by one and the ſame badge: &amp; though there be ſome other marks of them, whereby they may be diſcerned, as the outward profeſſion of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſeruice, and his holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yet there is one more ſpecial: now the badge that hee put vpon Chriſt Ieſus his eldeſt ſonne, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and trouble in this world: according to that that was propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.3.</note> he is deſpiſed, and reiected of men; he is a man full of ſorrowes, and hath experience of infirmities; he was oppreſſed and afflicted,<note place="margin">7.</note> yet did he not open his mouth; he is brought as a ſheepe to the ſlaughter, and as a ſheepe before the ſhearer is dumb, ſo he openeth not his mouth. The lord did break him,<note place="margin">10.</note> &amp; make him ſubiect vnto infirmities: all which we ſee verified in the Goſpel in the whole courſe of his life, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his death. Seeing this was the caſe of the firſt begotten, none of vs
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15176:79"/> the younger brethren muſt refuſe it, or be wearie of it.</p>
            <p>We ſee by experience, that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery family great is the prerogatiue and priuiledge of the eldeſt brother aboue all the reſt, he by the law of God was by his double portion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred aboue all the reſt: and Iacob in bleſſing all his children,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.3.</note> called Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben his eldeſt ſonne, The excellencie of dignitie, and the excellencie of power, and ſo did ſhew what belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vnto him as he was the eldeſt, if he had not loſt it, namely, that he ſhould haue beene the chiefeſt of all his brethren. None therefore muſt looke to goe beyond the eldeſt, nay all can not be like vnto him: and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the younger might come to as great an inheritance as he, by doing the ſame things that he did before them, though neuer ſo hard, and by going to it the ſame way, that he did, though full of many difficulties and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:15176:80" rendition="simple:additions"/> daungers; they might not with any colour refuſe the conditions, vnleſſe they would prepoſterouſly and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon preferre themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and thinke themſelues bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he.</p>
            <p>In like manner ſeeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith, to conſecrate the price of our ſaluation through afflictions, and he came vnto glorie no other way then this; we muſt thinke it good for vs to goe the ſame way, that we might be like vnto him, and ſo by our practiſe ſhew, that we acknowledge him to be the prince of our ſaluation, and our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt brother. Therefore as he is the moſt chief and principall in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or in the Church, or in a priuate family, or in any place els, whome all the reſt deſire to be like vnto: So when we are contented to be like vnto Chriſt in any thing, euen in the croſſe, then ſhall we declare
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15176:80"/> indeede that wee hold him not in word onely, but in true faith &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affection to be chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall aboue all others, and as was ſaid before, to be the Prince of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or as it is ſaide in this text that we haue in hand,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> The firſt begotten among many brethren.</p>
            <p>For indeede howſoeuer there is great difference betweene the head and the reſt of the members, and all of them are farre inferiour vnto it: yet there is and muſt be a certaine conformitie betweene the one and the other; that is, a certain likelihood and agreement betweene the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame bodie and the head: So howſoeuer there is no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betweene Chriſt and vs, yet we muſt thus farre agree with him, that we muſt not thinke to be aboue him, and therefore we muſt not refuſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny condition, that he hath vndergon before: vnleſſe we would moſt diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:15176:81"/> preferre our ſelues the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, before him our head: which thing to doe, were to darken the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of him that is the firſt borne, and to ſtaine the honour of him that is truly called, The Prince of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For what a confuſion were it in the commonwealth, if the Nobles, yea the meaneſt of the ſubiects would refuſe to doe that, which the King &amp; Prince had done before? or what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order wold there be in a family, if the yonger brethren ſhould think much and diſdaine to be brought vp that way, that the heire of the houſe had beene before: Euen ſo when we ſhall refuſe to beare the croſſe, which our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus by the appointment of his father hath born in greater meaſure, then we ſhall or can: it is nothing els but pride and ſelfe loue to lift vp our ſelues aboue him, and to ſay by our deedes, that we
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15176:81"/> will not in this thing be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto him, as to our Prince or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt brother.</p>
            <p>And then conſider I pray you, what an intolerable thing this were, that we beeing worſe then duſt and aſhes, and wormes meat, yea nothing els but a lumpe of ſinne, ſhould deſire to be ſpared aboue the onely ſonne of God, whome he hath made heire of all things;<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> by whome alſo he made the worlds; who is the brightnes of the glorie, and the ingrauen forme of his perſon, bearing vp all things by his mightie power: and is made ſo much the more excellent then the Angels, in as much as he hath obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a more excellent name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they: for of him he ſaith, Thou art my ſon, this day haue I begotten thee: and of the other, Let all the Angels of God worſhip him, as the Apoſtle doth moſt excellently ſhew at large in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes. Therefore
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15176:82"/> let vs not ſo loue our ſelues that the eſtate of Chriſt Ieſus ſhould ſeeme vnmeete for vs: as if he beeing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all afflictions and temptations brought vnto glory, we ſhould dream of a more eaſie way for our ſelues, and thinke to come to it after a more peaceable &amp; quiet manner, we know not what.</p>
            <p>But rather let this comfort and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold vs in all trouble and aduerſitie, that we can neuer be preſſed downe ſo low with it, but that Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Prince hath been more deepely plunged in it before: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more that we ſuffer, the more like we are vnto him. In ſo much that if it were poſſible for vs to haue the afflictions of <hi>Iob</hi> doubled vpon vs, yea if we could goe downe into hell, and ſo ſuffer all the torments of a damned and deſperate creature both in ſoule and bodie; hauing the worme of our conſcience knawing in vs continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15176:82"/> euen in them we ſhould be moſt like vnto Chriſt in his fearefull ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and deadly ſorrow that he fell into, complaining that his ſoule was heauie euen vnto the death:<note place="margin">Math 26.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and in his bloodie ſweat, by which all the parts of this bodie were ſtrained to the full: yea in the lamentable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries that he made vpon the croſſe, when as he finding no comfort in heauen nor in earth for a while he cried with a loud voice, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me,<note place="margin">&amp; 27.46.</note> and ſo gaue vp the ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But if all this doe not ſuffice vs, and we further demaund, why the Lord ſhould appoint ſo hard a way for vs vnto ſaluation, and why he ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine the gate to be ſo ſtrait,<note place="margin">&amp; 7.14.</note> and the way ſo narrow, whereby we ſhould enter into life: and ſo ſhould fooliſhly wiſh, as many doe, that he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſome eaſier way then this. Firſt of all I muſt ſay, as the Apoſtle
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15176:83"/> doth,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.20.</note> O man, who art thou, which pleadeſt againſt God? ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it; why haſt thou appointed me to doe ſo and ſo? we muſt not preſcribe any thing vnto the Lord in the courſe and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our ſaluation: no more then children muſt preſcribe vnto their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts after what maner they ſhould come to their inheritances and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But ſeeing that the ioyes of the kingdome of heauen are ſo great, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> as the eye hath not ſeene, nor the eare hath heard, neither haue they entred into the heart of man; and that we are altogether ſo vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt thinke our ſelues happie, if we come to inioy them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way at the laſt, be it neuer ſo hard; yea, if we ſhould goe to heauen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the midſt of hell.</p>
            <p>For when we are come thither, in the preſence of God is the fulnes of ioy,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> &amp; at his right hand are pleaſures
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15176:83"/> for euermore, we ſhall finde them ſo farr to exceed all that euer we heard, read, or thought of them: ſo that we ſhall ſay of them, as the Queene of Sheba ſaide of the wiſdome and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of king Salomon, when ſhe ſaw it: It was a true word,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 9.5.</note> which I heard in mine owne land of thy acts, and of thy wiſdome: howbeit I beleeued not their report, vntill I came, and mine eyes had ſeene it: and behold not the one halfe of thy great wiſdome was told me: for thou exceedeſt the fame that I heard: happie are thy men, and happie are theſe thy ſeruants, which ſtand before thee alway, &amp;c. So we ſhall finde all things there to ſurpaſſe all that euer we heard, &amp; ſo ſhal count our ſelues and other happie &amp; thriſe happy, that may ſtand in the preſence of God for euer.</p>
            <p>At what time we ſhall finde the happines of that life in many degrees to ſurmount all the troubles and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15176:84"/> that we haue ſuffered in this life, to ſurmount them I ſay both in greatnes, and in continuance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interruption. As the Apoſtle ſaith, who had ſo great experience of all kind of afflictions, that he ſaith of himſelfe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.8.</note> We are afflicted on euery ſide; and euery where we beare about in our bodie the dying of the Lord Ieſus: for we are alwaies deliuered vnto death for Ieſus ſake: yet he ſaith, he did not faint vnder them: for when he conſidered of the ioyes of heauen, and compared the afflictions of this world with them, he accounted the afflictions to be but ſhort, euen for a moment of time, and very light and eaſie, in reſpect of the eternall glorie, and the great waight of it, that was prepared for him, and for others: when he ſaith,<note place="margin">17.</note> for our light affliction, which is but for a moment cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall waight of glorie: and as he
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15176:84"/> deliuereth it in an other place more plainly &amp; confidently in theſe words: I count,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> or all things being well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, I gather, that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthie of the glorie which ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And then we ſhall neuer repent vs of the hardnes of the way, by which we came through manifold afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto ſo great and eternall glorie; no more then the ſicke patient is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that by induring ſo many hard things vnder the phyſitians hands, he attained vnto perfect health at the laſt. But rather as it was a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto Ioſeph,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.5.</note> to ſee what great honour he was come vnto in Egypt, ſo that he was made lord of all the countrey, though he had ſuffered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hard things before: according to that, that is ſaid in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.17</note> Ioſeph was ſold for a ſlaue; they held his feet in the ſtockes, &amp; he was laid in irons,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15176:85"/> vntill his appointed time came, and the counſell of the Lord had tried him. Then the King ſent, and looſed him, euen the ruler of the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him: he made him Lord of his houſe, and ruler of all his ſubſtance. So it ſhall be a comfort vnto vs for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer, that by walking in the ſtraite way of godlines, and induring many grieuous things in the ſame, we are come to that place where we are made Kings &amp; Queenes to raigne with Chriſt in glorie world without ende.</p>
            <p>And as Iacob was not ſorie, that he came to inherite his fathers bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at the laſt by induring a long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fathers houſe by the ſpace of twentie yeares, and a tedious kind of ſeruice vnder his cruell maſter <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> who did often change his wages, and cauſed him to be pinched with the froſt in the night, and to be ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the heate of the ſunne in
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:15176:85"/> the day. So it ſhall be no griefe of heart at all vnto vs then, that by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnder many croſſes here, we are come to inherit the bleſſing of our heauenly father in the kingdome of heauen, which was prepared for vs before the foundation of the world. But as the Iſraelites when they were quietly poſſeſſed of the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, that good land that flowed with milke and honie, for ioy thereof neuer remembred their long iorney trauailing by the ſpace of fourtie yeares through a vaſt deſart and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne wildernes, in which ſometimes they wanted water, ſometimes food, ſometimes were in daunger of their enemies, ſometimes were ſtung with fierie ſerpents, and ſometimes were put in great feare of other calamities: So wee when wee are come to that land of promiſe, whereof this was out a type and figure; where is the tree of life indeed,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.2.</note> bearing fruit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15176:86"/> whoſe fruit are for meat, and whoſe leaues are for medicine: where ſhall be no more curſe, but the throne of God, and of the lambe ſhall be in it, where his ſeruants ſhall ſerue him, and they ſhall ſee his face, and his name ſhall be in their foreheads: and there ſhall be no night there, &amp; they ſhall neede no candle, neither light of the ſunne: for the Lord God ſhall giue them light, and they ſhall raigne for euermore. Then all things that we haue ſuffered in theſe daies of our pilgrimage ſhall be cleane forgotten, and remembred no more.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him, that he came to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Iſrael at the ende of many yeares, in which he ſuffered ſo many hard things vnder the tyrannie of <hi>Saul,</hi> as he did; when as ſometimes he would haue ſmit him through with his ſpeare vnto the wall,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> and at an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time he would haue ſlain him in
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15176:86"/> his bed: and continually he hunted after his life,<note place="margin">&amp; 26.20.</note> as one would hunt a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge in the wildernes: So we ſhall not repent vs, that we are come to the kingdome of heauen after many yeares, in which ſometimes we haue beene purſued of one affliction, and ſometimes of an other: ſo that all our life long hath beene nothing els but a continuall warrefare with our own corruptions, and with the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world, and of the deuill. Therefore to vphold our ſelues in a good courſe, and that in all trialls we might poſſeſſe our ſoules in patience unto the ende, we muſt conſider and ſeriouſly meditate vpon the happines of the life to come: which ſhall ſo ſweeten the bitterneſſe of all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that either we ſhall not feele it in compariſon, or it ſhal ſeeme nothing unto vs: and ſo let vs put that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Apoſtle in practiſe, Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not be wearie of well doing,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> for in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15176:87"/> due ſeaſon we ſhall reape, if we faint not.</p>
            <p>Where to perſwade the Galatians and vs to go on co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly in all good courſes vnto the end, he makes a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of great reward which God will beſtow vpon all them that ſhall ſo doe, not ſo much in this life, as the life to come, when euery man ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things that are done in his bodie,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> according to that he hath done, whether it be good or euill: and this he doth by a familiar and plaine compariſon; That as the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man though the ſeede-time be very painefull and coſtly vnto him; ſo that both he buies his corne at a great price, and hath many an hard iourney at the plow, and meetes with many a boiſterous ſtorme, yet he giues not ouer in the midſt, but comforts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the hope of harueſt, which in due time will come, though long after: and is perſwaded, that that will
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15176:87"/> fully quite all his coſt, and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence all his labour to the full: and when he hath gathered his corne into his barne, he repents himſelfe not one whit of his coſt, or trauell, but rather is glad that by neither of them he was diſcouraged from following of that good courſe, which now he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be ſo gainfull vnto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>So we in all afflictions and in all difficulties continuing in well doing, muſt comfort our ſelues with the hope of that reward, that God hath promiſed in the kingdom of heauen: according to that, that is ſaid in the Pſalme, they that ſow in teares,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.5.</note> ſhall reape in ioy; they went out weeping, and caried pretious ſeede, but they ſhal returne with ioy, and bring their ſheaues. Where the time of affliction is compared vnto a ſeede-time in a deare yeare, when poore men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſcarſitie and price of corne ſow it with teares: but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15176:88"/> in heauen is likened vnto the harueſt, when the increaſe is ſo great, that they reape &amp; carie in their corne with great ioy. This is that then, which we muſt ſet before our eyes, that we might patiently vndergo the hardnes of affliction, it beeing the readie way to bring vs to glorie.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Paul</hi> applieth vnto ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, whoſe condition of life, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of bondſeruants, and vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and vnchriſtian maſters in thoſe daies was very hard: and willeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to doe their duties conſcionably, as ſeruing the Lord, knowing that of him, they ſhall receiue their reward: when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Coloſſ 3.23.</note> Seruants be obedient vnto them that are your maſters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, in all things, not with eye ſeruice, as men pleaſers, but in ſinglenes of heart, pleaſing God: whatſoeuer ye doe, doe it heartily, as to the Lord, and not to men, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of the Lord ye ſhall receiue
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15176:88"/> the reward of the inheritance: for ye ſerue the Lord Chriſt. Thus he would haue them to go on in their callings chearefully, though they were very baſe and painfull, in hope of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that was prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the kingdome of heauen. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if not onely ſeruants, but all other men did beleeue that in all things they had to deale with God, and that he would reward them if they did well, though all other ſhould neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them, the hope of that might comfort them in all difficulties.</p>
            <p>And this made <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God to refuſe all the riches and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that he might haue inioyed in Egypt, as beeing the reputed ſonne of Pharaohs daughter, and to chooſe rather to ioyne himſelfe with the people of God though in great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> becauſe he had reſpect vnto the recompence of the reward. Which reward could not then be ſeene, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15176:89"/> therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that he did it by faith: and truly if we did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that great reward that is laid vp in heauen for them that ſerue God, and is offered vnto vs in his word, if all the pleaſures of the world were laid before vs on the one hand, and all the afflictions of the ſame on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, we ſhould be of <hi>Moſes</hi> his minde; to chooſe rather to ſuffer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie with the people of God, then to indure the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon: eſteeming the rebuke of Chriſt greater riches, then all the treaſures of the world, becauſe by faith we haue reſpect vnto the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of that reward.</p>
            <p>And ſo I may conclude with that moſt excellent exhortation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the chapter following: Wherefore let vs alſo,<note place="margin">chap. 12.1.</note> ſeeing that we are compaſſed about with ſo great a cloud of witneſſes, caſt away euery thing that preſſeth downe, and the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:15176:89"/> ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on: let vs runne with patience the race, that is ſet before vs, looking vnto Ieſus the author and finiſher of our faith: who for the ioy that was ſet before him, indured the croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet at the right hand of the throne of God. Where he ſets before our eyes the example of our Sauiour Chriſt, who in thoſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous agonies he was in, to ſweeten the bitternes of his croſſe, did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly conſider of the ioy and glorie, which a little after he was to enter into: that we might alſo in our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings hold our thoughts ſeriouſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meditation of the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and for them indure them, and treade vnder our feete for them all the ſhame, reproach, and contempt of the world, that ſhall be caſt vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Where alſo that we might not faint vnder the burden, we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15176:90"/> of the circumſtance of time, when we ſhall reape the fruit of our labours,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that is, In due ſeaſon, if we faint not. Which is partly in this life, for godlineſſe hath the promiſes of this life,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as well as of the life to come: and the Lord as he doth in this life giue to his children the firſt fruits of his Spirit:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> ſo he doth giue them the firſt fruits of their labours, as a taſt of their happines, which they ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy more fully hereafter: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſaith in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mark. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> that he will reward thoſe that are his an hundred fold in this life. But this due time is meant principally of the life to come, when they ſhall receiue their reward fully: not onely in the houre of death, when the ſoule en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into happines, as it is ſaide of Lazarus, that when he died, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels caried his ſoule into Abrahams boſome:<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note> but eſpecially at the day of iudgement, when ſoule and bodie
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:15176:90"/> beeing ioyned together, they ſhall be in full poſſeſſion of eternal glorie and felicitie for euer.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Lord hath of his wiſdome and goodnes ſet downe the time, when we ſhall be comforted &amp; receiue our reward; we muſt in faith and patience waite vpon him for it. And as the husbandman that hath ſowne his field, doth not looke for his croppe the next day, or the next weeke, but tarieth till the harueſt come; ſo muſt we ſow the ſeede of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto God, euen vnder the croſſe, though with teares, and looke for the fruit of it at the great day of harueſt, when we ſhall reape it with ioy, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with that ioy that is vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and moſt glorious: when he ſhal ſeparate the ſheepe from the goates, and giue them their reward, ſaying, Come ye bleſſed of my father,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> take the inheritance of the kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you, from the foundation
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15176:91"/> of the world.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Lord hath beene patient in waiting for our amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from day to day: let vs patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect the accompliſhment of this his gratious promiſe from day to day, and from yeare to yeare. Setting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the example of the dumbe creatures, which expect with a feruent deſire to be deliuered from that bondage and corruption,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 8.19.</note> that now they are in, into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the ſonnes of God: and this they doe with ſtretching forth their heads, as the Apoſtle ſaith, like vnto the poore priſoner, that is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and puts out his head at the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon window, looking for the gratious pardon of the Prince. And if we can thus doe, as we ſhall not be fruſtrate of our hope,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo it ſhall maruelouſly vphold vs, as an ankor fixed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and not in earth, in all the waues and tempeſts of this troubleſome
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:15176:91"/> world, till we ariue happily at the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of heauen, we ſhall find the ioyes ſo to exceede all the miſeries that we haue indured here, that we ſhall not be grieued one whit, that we are come to ſuch a place of reſt, by ſo long and tedious a iourney: Which grace God graunt vnto vs, for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
